<!-- $NetBSD: configuring.xml,v 1.2 2005/06/11 16:31:40 dillo Exp $ -->

<chapter id="configuring">
<title>Configuring pkgsrc</title>

<!-- General configuration -->
<!--	DISTDIR -->
<!--	PACKAGES -->
<!--	WRKOBJDIR -->
<!--	FAILOVER_FETCH -->

<!-- Compiler settings -->
<!--	PKGSRC_COMPILER -->
<!--	CFLAGS -->

<!-- Configuration files -->
<!--	PKG_SYSCONFBASE -->
<!--	PKG_SYSCONFDIR.foobar -->

<!-- Security -->
<!--	ALLOW_VULNERABLE_PACKAGES -->
<!--	PKGVULNDIR -->

<!-- Developer/advanced settings -->
<!--	IGNORE_RECOMMENDED -->
<!--	PKG_DEVELOPER -->

<!-- pkginstall-related variables -->
<!--	PKG_REGISTER_SHELLS -->
<!--	PKG_RCD_SCRIPTS -->

<sect1 id="selecting-options">
<title>Selecting Build Options</title>

<para>Some packages have build time options, usually to select between
different dependencies, enable optional support for big dependencies
or enable experimental features.</para>

<para>To see which options, if any, a package supports, and which
options are mutually exclusive, run <command>make show-options</command>,
for example:</para>

<programlisting>
The following options are supported by this package:
        ssl      Enable SSL support.
Exactly one of the following gecko options is required:
        firefox  Use firefox as gecko rendering engine.
        mozilla  Use mozilla as gecko rendering engine.
At most one of the following database options may be selected:
        mysql    Enable support for MySQL database.
        pgsql    Enable support for PostgreSQL database.

These options are enabled by default: firefox
These options are currently enabled: mozilla ssl
</programlisting>

<para>The following variables can be defined in
<filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> to select which options to enable
for a package: <varname>PKG_DEFAULT_OPTIONS</varname>, which can be
used to select or disable options for all packages that support them,
and <varname>PKG_OPTIONS.<replaceable>pkgbase</replaceable></varname>,
which can be used to select or disable options specifically for
package <replaceable>pkgbase</replaceable>.  Options listed in these
variables are selected, options preceded by <quote>-</quote> are
disabled.</para>

<para>The following settings are consulted in the order given, and the
last setting that selects or disables an option is used:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>the default options as suggested by the package
maintainer</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>the options implied by the settings of legacy
variables (see below)</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><varname>PKG_DEFAULT_OPTIONS</varname></para></listitem>

<listitem><para><varname>PKG_OPTIONS.<replaceable>pkgbase</replaceable></varname></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>For groups of mutually exclusive options, the last option
selected is used, all others are automatically disabled.  If an option
of the group is explicitly disabled, the previously selected option,
if any, is used.  It is an error if no option from a required group of
options is selected, and building the package will fail.</para>

<para>Before the options framework was introduced, build options were
selected by setting a variable in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>
for each option.  To ease transition to the options framework for the
user, these legacy variables are converted to the appropriate options
setting automatically.  A warning is issued to prompt the user to
update <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> to use the options framework
directly.  Support for these legacy variables will be removed
eventually.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
