<!-- $NetBSD: creating.xml,v 1.4 2006/10/21 11:58:18 rillig Exp $ -->

<chapter id="creating">
<title>Creating a new pkgsrc package from scratch</title>

<para>When you find a package that is not yet in pkgsrc, you
most likely have a URL from where you can download the source
code. Starting with this URL, creating a package involves only a
few steps.</para>

<procedure>

<step><para>First, install the packages <filename
role="pkg">pkgtools/url2pkg</filename> and <filename
role="pkg">pkgtools/pkglint</filename>.</para></step>
	
<step><para>Then, choose one of the top-level directories as the
category in which you want to place your package. You can also create a
directory of your own (maybe called <filename>local</filename>). In that
category directory, create another directory for your package and change
into it.</para></step>

<step><para>Run the program <command>url2pkg</command>, which will ask
you for a URL. Enter the URL of the distribution file (in most cases a
<filename>.tar.gz</filename> file) and watch how the basic ingredients
of your package are created automatically. The distribution file is
extracted automatically to fill in some details in the
<filename>Makefile</filename> that would otherwise have to be done
manually.</para></step>

<step><para>Examine the extracted files to determine the dependencies of
your package. Ideally, this is mentioned in some
<filename>README</filename> file, but things may differ. For each of
these dependencies, look where it exists in pkgsrc, and if there is a
file called <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> in that directory, add a
line to your package <filename>Makefile</filename> which includes that
file just before the last line. If the
<filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file does not exist, add a
<varname>DEPENDS</varname> line to the Makefile, which specifies the
version of the dependency and where it can be found in pkgsrc. This line
should be placed in the third paragraph. If the dependency is only
needed for building the package, but not when using it, use
<varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname> instead of <varname>DEPENDS</varname>.
Your package may then look like this:</para>

<programlisting>
    [...]

    BUILD_DEPENDS+= lua>=5.0:../../lang/lua
    DEPENDS+=       screen-[0-9]*:../../misc/screen
    DEPENDS+=       screen>=4.0:../../misc/screen

    [...]

    .include "../../<replaceable>category</replaceable>/<replaceable>package</replaceable>/buildlink3.mk"
    .include "../../devel/glib2/buildlink3.mk"
    .include "../../mk/bsd.pkg.mk"
</programlisting>

</step>

<step><para>Run <command>pkglint</command> to see what things still need
to be done to make your package a <quote>good</quote> one. If you don't
know what pkglint's warnings want to tell you, try <command>pkglint
--explain</command> or <command>pkglint
-e</command>, which outputs additional
explanations.</para></step>

<step><para>In many cases the package is not yet ready to build. You can
find instructions for the most common cases in the next section, <xref
linkend="creating.common"/>. After you have followed the instructions
over there, you can hopefully continue here.</para></step>

<step><para>Run <command>bmake clean</command> to clean the working
directory from the extracted files. Besides these files, a lot of cache
files and other system information has been saved in the working
directory, which may become wrong after you edited the
<filename>Makefile</filename>.</para></step>

<step><para>Now, run <command>bmake</command> to build the package. For
the various things that can go wrong in this phase, consult <xref
linkend="fixes"/>.</para></step>

<step><para>When the package builds fine, the next step is to install
the package. Run <command>bmake install</command> and hope that
everything works.</para></step>

<step><para>Up to now, the file <filename>PLIST</filename>, which
contains a list of the files that are installed by the package, is
nearly empty. Run <command>bmake print-PLIST
&gt;PLIST</command> to generate a probably correct list. Check
the file using your preferred text editor to see if the list of
files looks plausible.</para></step>

<step><para>Run <command>pkglint</command> again to see if the generated
<filename>PLIST</filename> contains garbage or not.</para></step>

<step><para>When you ran <command>bmake install</command>, the package
has been registered in the database of installed files, but with an
empty list of files. To fix this, run <command>bmake deinstall</command>
and <command>bmake install</command> again. Now the package is
registered with the list of files from
<filename>PLIST</filename>.</para></step>

<step><para>Run <command>bmake package</command> to create a binary
package from the set of installed files.</para></step>

</procedure>

<sect1 id="creating.common">
<title>Common types of packages</title>

<sect2 id="creating.perl-module">
<title>Perl modules</title>

<para>Simple Perl modules are handled automatically by
<command>url2pkg</command>, including dependencies.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="creating.kde-app">
<title>KDE applications</title>

<para>KDE applications should always include
<filename>meta-pkgs/kde3/kde3.mk</filename>, which contains numerous
settings that are typical of KDE packages.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>
</chapter>
