<!-- $NetBSD: fixes.xml,v 1.14 2005/05/14 22:34:59 rillig Exp $ -->

<chapter id="fixes"> <?dbhtml filename="fixes.html"?>
  <title>Notes on fixes for packages</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>General operation</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>How to pull in variables from /etc/mk.conf</title>
    
      <para> The problem with package-defined variables that can be
        overridden via <varname>MAKECONF</varname> or
        <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> is that &man.make.1; expands a
        variable as it is used, but evaluates preprocessor like
        statements (.if, .ifdef and .ifndef) as they are read.  So, to
        use any variable (which may be set in
        <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>) in one of the .if*
        statements, the file <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> must be
        included before that .if* statement.  </para>
    
      <para> Rather than have a number of ad-hoc ways of including
        <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>, should it exist, or
        <varname>MAKECONF</varname>, should it exist, include the
        <filename>pkgsrc/mk/bsd.prefs.mk</filename> file in the package
        Makefile before any preprocessor-like .if, .ifdef, or .ifndef
        statements: </para>
    
      <programlisting>.include "../../mk/bsd.prefs.mk"
    
    .if defined(USE_MENUS)
      ...
    .endif</programlisting>
    
      <para>  If you wish to set the <varname>CFLAGS</varname> variable
        in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> please make sure to use: 
    
        <programlisting>CFLAGS+=  -your -flags</programlisting>
    
        Using <varname>CFLAGS=</varname> (i.e. without the
        <quote>+</quote>) may lead to problems with packages that need
        to add their own flags.  Also, you may want to take a look at
        the <pkg>devel/cpuflags</pkg> package if you're interested in
        optimization for the current CPU.  </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Restricted packages</title>
    
      <para> Some licenses restrict how software may be re-distributed.
        In order to satisfy these restrictions, the package system
        defines five make variables that can be set to note these
        restrictions: </para>
    
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>RESTRICTED</varname></para>
          
          <para> This variable should be set whenever a restriction
            exists (regardless of its kind).  Set this variable to a
            string containing the reason for the restriction.  </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem> 
          <para><varname>NO_BIN_ON_CDROM</varname></para>
          
          <para>     Binaries may not be placed on CD-ROM.  Set this
            variable to     <varname>${RESTRICTED}</varname> whenever a
            binary package may not     be included on a CD-ROM.  </para> 
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>NO_BIN_ON_FTP</varname></para>
          
          <para>     Binaries may not be placed on an FTP server.  Set
            this     variable to <varname>${RESTRICTED}</varname>
            whenever a binary package     may not not be made available
            on the Internet.  </para> 
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>NO_SRC_ON_CDROM</varname></para>
          
          <para> Distfiles may not be placed on CD-ROM.  Set this
            variable to <varname>${RESTRICTED}</varname> if
            re-distribution of the source code or other distfile(s) is
            not allowed on CD-ROMs.  </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para><varname>NO_SRC_ON_FTP</varname></para>
          
          <para> Distfiles may not be placed on FTP.  Set this variable
            to <varname>${RESTRICTED}</varname> if re-distribution of
            the source code or other distfile(s) via the Internet is not
            allowed.  </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    
      <para> Please note that the use of <varname>NO_PACKAGE</varname>,
        <varname>IGNORE</varname>, <varname>NO_CDROM</varname>, or other
        generic make variables to denote restrictions is deprecated,
        because they unconditionally prevent users from generating
        binary packages!  </para>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2 id="dependencies">
      <title>Handling dependencies</title>
    
      <para> Your package may depend on some other package being present
        - and there are various ways of expressing this
        dependency. pkgsrc supports the <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname>
        and <varname>DEPENDS</varname> definitions, as well as
        dependencies via <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename>, which is
        the preferred way to handle dependencies, and which uses the
        variables named above. See <xref linkend="buildlink"/> for more
        information. </para> 
    
      <para> The basic difference between the two variables is as
        follows: The <varname>DEPENDS</varname> definition registers
        that pre-requisite in the binary package so it will be pulled in
        when the binary package is later installed, whilst the
        <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname> definition does not, marking a
        dependency that is only needed for building the package.
        </para>
    
      <para> This means that if you only need a package present whilst
        you are building, it should be noted as a
        <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname>.  </para>
    
      <para> The format for a <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname> and a
        <varname>DEPENDS</varname> definition is: </para>
    
      <programlisting>&lt;pre-req-package-name&gt;:../../&lt;category&gt;/&lt;pre-req-package&gt;</programlisting>
    
      <para> Please note that the <quote>pre-req-package-name</quote>
        may include any of the wildcard version numbers recognized by
        &man.pkg.info.1;.  </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> If your package needs another package's binaries or
            libraries to build or run, and if that package has a
            <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file available, use it:
            </para>

            <programlisting>
    .include "../../graphics/jpeg/buildlink3.mk"
    </programlisting>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> If your package needs to use another package to build
            itself and there is no <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename>
            file available, use the <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname>
            definition: </para>
    
          <programlisting>BUILD_DEPENDS+=  autoconf-2.13:../../devel/autoconf</programlisting>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> If your package needs a library with which to link and
            again there is no <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file
            available, this is specified using the
            <varname>DEPENDS</varname> definition.  An example of this
            is the <pkg>print/lyx</pkg> package, which uses the xpm
            library, version 3.4j to build: </para>
    
          <programlisting>DEPENDS+=       xpm-3.4j:../../graphics/xpm</programlisting>
    
          <para> You can also use wildcards in package dependences:
            </para>
    
          <programlisting>DEPENDS+=       xpm-[0-9]*:../../graphics/xpm</programlisting>
    
          <para> Note that such wildcard dependencies are retained when
            creating binary packages.  The dependency is checked when
            installing the binary package and any package which matches
            the pattern will be used.  Wildcard dependencies should be
            used with care.  </para>
    
          <para> The <quote>-[0-9]*</quote> should be used instead of
            <quote>-*</quote> to avoid potentially ambiguous matches
            such as <quote>tk-postgresql</quote> matching a
            <quote>tk-*</quote> <varname>DEPENDS</varname>.  </para>
    
          <para>Wildcards can also be used to specify that a package
            will only  build against a certain minimum version of a
            pre-requisite: </para>
              
          <programlisting>DEPENDS+=       tiff>=3.5.4:../../graphics/tiff</programlisting>
    
          <para> This means that the package will build against version
            3.5.4 of the tiff library or newer.  Such a dependency may
            be warranted if, for example, the API of the library has
            changed with version 3.5.4 and a package would not compile
            against an earlier version of tiff.  </para>
    
          <para>  Please note that such dependencies should only be
            updated if a package requires  a newer pre-requisite, but
            not to denote recommendations such as security  updates or
            ABI changes that do not prevent a package from building
            correctly.  Such recommendations can be expressed using
            <varname>RECOMMENDED</varname>: </para>
    
          <programlisting>RECOMMENDED+=   tiff>=3.6.1:../../graphics/tiff</programlisting>
    
          <para> In addition to the above <varname>DEPENDS</varname>
            line, this denotes that while a package will build against
            tiff&gt;=3.5.4, at least version 3.6.1 is recommended.
            <varname>RECOMMENDED</varname> entries will be turned into
            dependencies unless explicitly ignored (in which case a
            warning will be printed).  Packages that are built with
            recommendations ignored may not be uploaded to
            ftp.NetBSD.org by developers and should not be used across
            different systems that may have different versions of binary
            packages installed.  </para>
    
          <para> For security fixes, please update the package
            vulnerabilities file as well as setting
            <varname>RECOMMENDED</varname>, see <xref
            linkend="security-handling"/> for more
            information. </para> 
	</listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> If your package needs some executable to be able to run
            correctly and if there's no
            <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file, this is specified
            using the <varname>DEPENDS</varname> variable. The
            <pkg>print/lyx</pkg> package needs to be able to execute the
            latex binary from the teTeX package when it runs, and that
            is specified: </para>
    
          <programlisting>DEPENDS+=        teTeX-[0-9]*:../../print/teTeX</programlisting>
    
          <para>  The comment about wildcard dependencies from previous
            paragraph  applies here, too.  </para> 
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    
      <para> If your package needs files from another package to build,
        see the first part of the <quote>do-configure</quote> target
        <pkg>print/ghostscript5</pkg> package (it relies on the jpeg
        sources being present in source form during the build): </para>
    
      <programlisting>if [ ! -e ${_PKGSRCDIR}/graphics/jpeg/${WRKDIR:T}/jpeg-6b ]; then \
          cd ${_PKGSRCDIR}/../../graphics/jpeg &amp;&amp; ${MAKE} extract;              \
    fi</programlisting>
    
      <para> If you build any other packages that way, please make sure
        the working files are deleted too when this package's working
        files are cleaned up.  The easiest way to do so is by adding a
        pre-clean target: </para>
    
      <programlisting>pre-clean:
          cd ${_PKGSRCDIR}/../../graphics/jpeg &amp;&amp; ${MAKE} clean</programlisting>
    
      <para> Please also note the <varname>BUILD_USES_MSGFMT</varname>
        and <varname>BUILD_USES_GETTEXT_M4</varname> definitions, which
        are provided as convenience definitions.  The former works out
        whether &man.msgfmt.1; is part of the base system, and, if it isn't,
        installs the <pkg>devel/gettext</pkg> package.  The latter adds
        a build dependency on either an installed version of an older
        gettext package, or if it isn't, installs the
        <pkg>devel/gettext-m4</pkg> package.  </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Handling conflicts with other packages</title>
    
      <para> Your package may conflict with other packages a user might
        already have installed on his system, e.g. if your package
        installs the same set of files like another package in our
        pkgsrc tree.  </para>
    
      <para> In this case you can set <varname>CONFLICTS</varname> to a
        space separated list of packages (including version string) your
        package conflicts with.  </para>
    
      <para> For example <pkg>x11/Xaw3d</pkg> and <pkg>x11/Xaw-Xpm</pkg>
        install provide the same shared library, thus you set in
        <filename>pkgsrc/x11/Xaw3d/Makefile</filename>: </para>
    
      <programlisting>CONFLICTS=      Xaw-Xpm-[0-9]*</programlisting>
    
      <para> and in <filename>pkgsrc/x11/Xaw-Xpm/Makefile</filename>:
        </para>
    
      <programlisting>CONFLICTS=      Xaw3d-[0-9]*</programlisting>
    
      <para>  Packages will automatically conflict with other packages
        with the name prefix  and a different version
        string. <quote>Xaw3d-1.5</quote> e.g. will automatically
        conflict  with the older version <quote>Xaw3d-1.3</quote>.
        </para> 
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Packages that cannot or should not be built</title>
    
      <para>
        There are several reasons why a package might be instructed to not
        build under certain circumstances. If the package builds and runs
        on most platforms, the exceptions should be noted with
        <varname>NOT_FOR_PLATFORM</varname>.  If the package builds and
        runs on a small handful of platforms, set
        <varname>ONLY_FOR_PLATFORM</varname> instead. If the package
        should be skipped (for example, because it provides functionality
        already provided by the system), set
        <varname>PKG_SKIP_REASON</varname> to a descriptive message. If
        the package should fail because some preconditions are not met,
        set <varname>PKG_FAIL_REASON</varname> to a descriptive message.
        </para> 
    
      <para> <varname>IGNORE</varname> is deprecated because it didn't
        provide enough information to determine whether the build should
        fail. 
      </para>  
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages which should not be deleted, once installed</title>
    
      <para>To ensure that a package may not be deleted, once it has been
        installed, the <varname>PKG_PRESERVE</varname> definition should
        be set in the package Makefile. This will be carried into any
        binary package that is made from this pkgsrc entry. A
        <quote>preserved</quote> package will 
        not be deleted using &man.pkg.delete.1; unless the
        <quote>-f</quote> option is used. </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2 id="security-handling">
      <title>Handling packages with security problems</title>
      
      <para> When a vulnerability is found, this should be noted in
        <filename>localsrc/security/advisories/pkg-vulnerabilities</filename>,
        and after the commit of that file, it should be copied to both
        <filename>/pub/NetBSD/packages/distfiles/pkg-vulnerabilities</filename>
        and
        <filename>/pub/NetBSD/packages/distfiles/vulnerabilities</filename>
        on ftp.NetBSD.org using
        <filename>localsrc/security/advisories/Makefile</filename>.  In
        addition, if a <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file exists
        for an affected package, bumping <varname>PKGREVISION</varname>
        and creating a corresponding
        <varname>BUILDLINK_RECOMMENDED.<replaceable>pkg</replaceable></varname>
        entry should be considered. See <xref linkend="buildlink"/> for
        more information about writing
        <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> files and
        <varname>BUILDLINK_*</varname> definitions. </para>

      <para> Also, if the fix should be applied to the stable pkgsrc
        branch, be sure to submit a pullup request!  </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>How to handle compiler bugs</title>
    
      <para>  Some source files trigger bugs in the compiler, based on
        combinations  of compiler version and architecture and almost
        always relation to  optimisation being enabled.  Common symptoms
        are gcc internal errors  or never finishing compiling a file.
        </para> 
    
      <para>  Typically a workaround involves testing the
        <varname>MACHINE_ARCH</varname>  and compiler version, disabling
        optimisation for that
        file/<varname>MACHINE_ARCH</varname>/compiler  combination, and
        documenting it in  <filename>pkgsrc/doc/HACKS</filename>.  See
        that file for a number of examples!  </para> 
    </sect2>
            

    <sect2>
      <title>How to handle incrementing versions when fixing an existing package</title>
    
      <para> When making fixes to an existing package it can be useful
        to change the version number in <varname>PKGNAME</varname>. To
        avoid conflicting with future versions by the original author, a
        <quote>nb1</quote>, <quote>nb2</quote>, ... suffix can be used
        on package versions by setting <varname>PKGREVISION=1</varname>
        (2, ...). The <quote>nb</quote> is treated like a
        <quote>.</quote> by the pkg tools. e.g.  </para>
    
      <programlisting>  DISTNAME= foo-17.42
    PKGREVISION=  9</programlisting>
    
      <para> will result in a <varname>PKGNAME</varname> of
        <quote>foo-17.42nb9</quote>.  </para>
    
      <para> When a new release of the package is released, the
        <varname>PKGREVISION</varname> should be removed. e.g. on a new
        minor release of the above package, things should be like:
        </para>
    
      <programlisting>DISTNAME=   foo-17.43</programlisting>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Portability of packages</title>

      <para>One appealing feature of pkgsrc is that it runs on many different
        platforms. As a result, it is important to ensure, where possible,
        that packages in pkgsrc are portable. There are some particular
        details you should pay attention to while working on pkgsrc.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>${INSTALL}, ${INSTALL_DATA_DIR}, ...</title>

        <para>The BSD-compatible <command>install</command> supplied with some
          operating systems will not perform more than one operation at a time.
          As such, you should call <quote>${INSTALL}</quote>, etc. like this:</para>

          <programlisting>${INSTALL_DATA_DIR} ${PREFIX}/dir1
${INSTALL_DATA_DIR} ${PREFIX}/dir2</programlisting>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Possible downloading issues</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Packages whose distfiles aren't available for plain downloading</title>
    
      <para> If you need to download from a dynamic URL you can set
        <varname>DYNAMIC_MASTER_SITES</varname> and a <command>make
        fetch</command> will call <filename>files/getsite.sh</filename>
        with the name of each file to download as an argument, expecting
        it to output the URL of the directory from which to download
        it. <pkg>graphics/ns-cult3d</pkg> is an example of this usage.
        </para>
    
      <para> If the download can't be automated, because the user must
        submit personal information to apply for a password, or must pay
        for the source, or whatever, you can set
        <varname>_FETCH_MESSAGE</varname> to a macro which displays a
        message explaining the
        situation. <varname>_FETCH_MESSAGE</varname> must be executable
        shell commands, not just a message. (Generally, it executes
        <varname>${ECHO}</varname>). As of this writing, the following
        packages use this: <pkg>audio/realplayer</pkg>,
        <pkg>cad/simian</pkg>, <pkg>devel/ipv6socket</pkg>,
        <pkg>emulators/vmware-module</pkg>,
        <pkg>fonts/acroread-jpnfont</pkg>,
        <pkg>sysutils/storage-manager</pkg>,
        <pkg>www/ap-aolserver</pkg>, <pkg>www/openacs</pkg>. Try to be
        consistent with them.  </para>
    </sect2>
    

    <sect2>
      <title>How to handle modified distfiles with the 'old' name</title>
    
      <para> Sometimes authors of a software package make some
        modifications after the software was released, and they put up a
        new distfile without changing the package's version number. If a
        package is already in pkgsrc at that time, the md5 checksum will
        no longer match. The correct way to work around this is to
        update the package's md5 checksum to match the package on the
        master site (beware, any mirrors may not be up to date yet!),
        and to remove the old distfile from
        ftp.NetBSD.org's
        <filename>/pub/NetBSD/packages/distfiles</filename> directory.
        Furthermore, a mail to the package's author seems appropriate
        making sure the distfile was really updated on purpose, and that
        no trojan horse or so crept in.  </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Configuration gotchas</title>

    <sect2 id="fixes.libtool">
      <title>Shared libraries - libtool</title>

      <para>pkgsrc supports many different machines, with different
        object formats like a.out and ELF, and varying abilities to do
        shared library and dynamic loading at all. To accompany this,
        varying commands and options have to be passed to the
        compiler, linker, etc. to get the Right Thing, which can be
        pretty annoying especially if you don't have all the machines
        at your hand to test things.  The <pkg>devel/libtool</pkg> pkg
        can help here, as it just <quote>knows</quote> how to build
        both static and dynamic libraries from a set of source files,
        thus being platform independent.</para>

      <para>Here's how to use libtool in a pkg in seven simple
        steps:</para> 

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Add <varname>USE_LIBTOOL=yes</varname> to the package
            Makefile.</para> 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For library objects, use <quote>${LIBTOOL} --mode=compile
            ${CC}</quote> in place of <quote>${CC}</quote>. You could even
            add it to the definition of <varname>CC</varname>, if only
            libraries are being built in a given Makefile. This one command
            will build both PIC and non-PIC library objects, so you need not
            have separate shared and non-shared library rules.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For the linking of the library, remove any
            <quote>ar</quote>, <quote>ranlib</quote>, and <quote>ld
            -Bshareable</quote> commands, and instead use:</para> 

          <programlisting>${LIBTOOL} --mode=link ${CC} -o ${.TARGET:.a=.la} ${OBJS:.o=.lo} -rpath ${PREFIX}/lib -version-info major:minor</programlisting>

          <para>Note that the library is changed to have a
            <filename>.la</filename> extension, and the objects are
            changed to have a <filename>.lo</filename>
            extension. Change <varname>OBJS</varname> as
            necessary. This automatically creates all of the
            <filename>.a</filename>,
            <filename>.so.major.minor</filename>, and ELF symlinks (if
            necessary) in the build directory. Be sure to include
            <quote>-version-info</quote>, especially when major and
            minor are zero, as libtool will otherwise strip off the
            shared library version.</para>

          <para> From the libtool manual:</para>

          <programlisting>
     So, libtool library versions are described by three integers:

CURRENT
       The most recent interface number that this library implements.

REVISION
       The implementation number of the CURRENT interface.

AGE
       The difference between the newest and oldest interfaces that this
       library implements.  In other words, the library implements all the
       interface numbers in the range from number `CURRENT - AGE' to
       `CURRENT'.
       
     If two libraries have identical CURRENT and AGE numbers, then the
dynamic linker chooses the library with the greater REVISION number. </programlisting>

          <para>The <quote>-release</quote> option will produce
            different results for a.out and ELF (excluding symlinks)
            in only one case. An ELF library of the form
            <quote>libfoo-release.so.<emphasis>x</emphasis>.<emphasis>y</emphasis></quote>
            will have a symlink of
            <quote>libfoo.so.<emphasis>x</emphasis>.<emphasis>y</emphasis></quote>
            on an a.out platform. This is handled
            automatically.</para>

          <para>The <quote>-rpath argument</quote> is the install
            directory of the library being built.</para>

          <para>In the <filename>PLIST</filename>, include only the
            <filename>.la</filename> file, the other files will be
	    added automatically.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When linking shared object (<filename>.so</filename>)
            files, i.e. files that are loaded via &man.dlopen.3;, NOT
            shared libraries, use <quote>-module
            -avoid-version</quote> to prevent them getting version
            tacked on.</para>

          <para>The <filename>PLIST</filename> file gets the
            <filename>foo.so</filename> entry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When linking programs that depend on these libraries
            <emphasis>before</emphasis> they are installed, preface
            the &man.cc.1; or &man.ld.1; line with <quote>${LIBTOOL}
            --mode=link</quote>, and it will find the correct
            libraries (static or shared), but please be aware that
            libtool will not allow you to specify a relative path in
            -L (such as <quote>-L../somelib</quote>), because it
            expects you to change that argument to be the
            <filename>.la</filename> file. e.g.</para>

          <programlisting>${LIBTOOL} --mode=link ${CC} -o someprog -L../somelib -lsomelib</programlisting>

          <para>should be changed to:</para>

          <programlisting>${LIBTOOL} --mode=link ${CC} -o <replaceable>someprog</replaceable> <replaceable>../somelib/somelib.la</replaceable></programlisting>

          <para>and it will do the right thing with the libraries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When installing libraries, preface the &man.install.1;
            or &man.cp.1; command with <quote>${LIBTOOL}
            --mode=install</quote>, and change the library name to
            <filename>.la</filename>. e.g.</para>

          <programlisting>${LIBTOOL} --mode=install ${BSD_INSTALL_DATA} ${SOMELIB:.a=.la} ${PREFIX}/lib</programlisting>

          <para>This will install the static <filename>.a</filename>,
            shared library, any needed symlinks, and run
            &man.ldconfig.8;.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para> In your <filename>PLIST</filename>, include only
            the <filename>.la</filename>
            file (this is a change from previous behaviour). </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2>
      <title>Using libtool on GNU packages that already support libtool</title>

      <para>Add <varname>USE_LIBTOOL=yes</varname> to the
        package Makefile. This will override the package's own libtool
        in most cases.  For older libtool using packages,  libtool is
        made by ltconfig script during the do-configure step; you can
        check the libtool script location by doing <command>make
        configure; find work*/ -name libtool</command>. </para>

      <para> <varname>LIBTOOL_OVERRIDE</varname> specifies which libtool
        scripts, relative to <varname>WRKSRC</varname>, to override.  By
        default, it is set to <quote>libtool */libtool
        */*/libtool</quote>.  If this does not match the location of the
        package's libtool script(s), set it as appropriate. </para>

      <para> If you do not need <filename>*.a</filename> static
        libraries built and installed, then use
        <varname>SHLIBTOOL_OVERRIDE</varname> instead. </para>

      <para>If your package makes use of the platform independent library
        for loading dynamic shared objects, that comes with libtool
        (libltdl), you should include devel/libltdl/buildlink3.mk.</para>

      <para>Some packages use libtool incorrectly so that the package may not work or
        build in some circumstances. Some of the more common errors are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The inclusion of a shared object (-module) as a dependent library in an
            executable or library. This in itself isn't a problem if one of two things
            has been done:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The shared object is named correctly, i.e.
                <filename>libfoo.la</filename>, not
                <filename>foo.la</filename></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The -dlopen option is used when linking an executable.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The use of libltdl without the correct calls to initialisation routines.
            The function lt_dlinit() should be called and the macro
            <varname>LTDL_SET_PRELOADED_SYMBOLS</varname> included in
            executables.</para> 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2>
      <title>GNU Autoconf/Automake</title>

      <para>If a package needs GNU autoconf or automake to be executed
        to regenerate the configure script and Makefile.in makefile
        templates, then they should be executed in a pre-configure
        target. Two Makefile fragments are provided in
        <filename>pkgsrc/mk/autoconf.mk</filename> and
        <filename>pkgsrc/mk/automake.mk</filename> to help
        dealing with these tools. See comments in these files for
        details.</para>

        <para> For packages that need only autoconf: </para>

        <programlisting>AUTOCONF_REQD=    2.50    # if default version is not good enough
...

pre-configure:
          cd ${WRKSRC}; ${AUTOCONF}

...
.include "../../mk/autoconf.mk"</programlisting>

        <para> and for packages that need automake and autoconf: </para> 

<programlisting>AUTOMAKE_REQD=  1.7.1   # if default version is not good enough
...

pre-configure:
          cd ${WRKSRC};                                           \
          ${ACLOCAL};                                             \
          ${AUTOHEADER};                                          \
          ${AUTOMAKE} -a --foreign -i;                            \
          ${AUTOCONF}

...
.include "../mk/automake.mk"</programlisting>

        <para> Packages which use GNU Automake will almost certainly
          require GNU Make, but that's automatically provided for you in
          <filename>mk/automake.mk</filename>. </para> 

        <para> There are times when the configure process makes
          additional  changes to the generated files, which then causes
          the build  process to try to re-execute the automake sequence.
          This is  prevented by touching various files in the configure
          stage. If  this causes problems with your package you can set
          <varname>AUTOMAKE_OVERRIDE=NO</varname> in the package
          Makefile. </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Building considerations</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>CPP defines</title>
    
      <para>
        To port an application to NetBSD, it's usually necessary for the
        compiler to be able to judge the system on which it's compiling, and
        we use definitions so that the C pre-processor can do this.
      </para>

      <para>
        To test whether you are working on a 4.4 BSD-derived system, you
        should use the BSD definition, which is defined in
        <filename>&lt;sys/param.h&gt;</filename> on said systems.
      </para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[#include <sys/param.h>]]></programlisting>

      <para>and then you can surround the BSD-specific parts of your
        package's C/C++ code using this conditional:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[#if (defined(BSD) && BSD >= 199306)
    ...
#endif]]></programlisting>

      <para>Please use the <quote>__NetBSD__</quote> definition sparingly - it
        should only apply to features of &os; that are not present in other
        4.4-lite derived BSDs.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Package specific actions</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Package configuration files</title>
      
      <para> Packages should be taught to look for their configuration
        files in <varname>${PKG_SYSCONFDIR}</varname>, which is passed
        through to the configure and build processes.
        <varname>PKG_SYSCONFDIR</varname> may be customized in various
        ways by setting other make variables: </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> <varname>PKG_SYSCONFBASE</varname> is the main config
            directory   under which all package configuration files are
            to be found.  This defaults to
            <filename>${PREFIX}/etc</filename>, but may  be overridden
            in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>.</para> 
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>  <varname>PKG_SYSCONFSUBDIR</varname> is the subdirectory of
            <varname>PKG_SYSCONFBASE</varname> under which the
            configuration files for a particular package may be found, e.g.
            the Apache configuration files may all be found under the
            <filename>httpd/</filename> subdirectory of
            <varname>${PKG_SYSCONFBASE}</varname>. This should be set in
            the package Makefile.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>     
          <para> By default,
            <varname>PKG_SYSCONFDIR</varname> is set to
            <varname>${PKG_SYSCONFBASE}/${PKG_SYSCONFSUBDIR}</varname>, 
            but this may be overridden by setting
            <varname>PKG_SYSCONFDIR.${PKG_SYSCONFVAR}</varname> for a
            particular package, where <varname>PKG_SYSCONFVAR</varname>
            defaults to <varname>${PKGBASE}</varname>. This is not meant to
            be set by a package Makefile, but is reserved for users who wish
            to override the <varname>PKG_SYSCONFDIR</varname> setting for
            a particular package with a special location.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para> The only variables that users should customize are
          <varname>PKG_SYSCONFBASE</varname> and  <varname>PKG_SYSCONFDIR.${PKG_SYSCONFVAR}</varname>.
          Users will typically want to set
          <varname>PKG_SYSCONFBASE</varname> to
          <filename>/etc</filename>, or to accept the default location
          of <filename>${PREFIX}/etc</filename>. </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>User interaction</title>

      <para>Occasionally, packages require interaction from the user, and this can be
        in a number of ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>help in fetching the distfiles</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>help to configure the package before it is built</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>help during the build process</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>help during the installation of a package</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The <varname>INTERACTIVE_STAGE</varname> definition is provided to notify
        the pkgsrc mechanism of an interactive stage which will be needed, and
        this should be set in the package's <filename>Makefile</filename>. e.g.</para>

      <programlisting>INTERACTIVE_STAGE= build</programlisting>

      <para>Multiple interactive stages can be specified:</para>

      <programlisting>INTERACTIVE_STAGE= configure install</programlisting>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Handling licenses</title>

      <para>A package may underly a license which the user has or has
        not agreed to accept. Usually, packages that underly
        well-known Open Source licenses (e.g. the GNU Public License,
        GPL) won't have any special license 
        tags added in pkgsrc which require special action by the user
        of such packages, but there are quite a number of other
        licenses out there that pkgsrc users may not be able to
        follow, for whatever reasons. For these cases, pkgsrc contains
        a mechanism to note that a package underlies a certain
        license, and the user has to accept the license before the
        package can be installed. </para>

      <para>
        Placing a certain package under a certain license works by
        setting the <varname>LICENSE</varname> variable to a string
        identifying the license, e.g. in <pkg>graphics/graphviz</pkg>:
        </para>

      <programlisting>LICENSE=        graphviz-license</programlisting>

      <para>
	When trying to build, the user will get a notice that the
        package underlies a license which he hasn't accepted (yet):
        </para>
	
      <programlisting>
&cprompt; <userinput>make</userinput>
===> graphviz-1.12 has an unacceptable license: graphviz-license.
===>     To build this package, add this line to your /etc/mk.conf:
===>     ACCEPTABLE_LICENSES+=graphviz-license
===>     To view the license, enter "/usr/bin/make show-license".
*** Error code 1</programlisting>

        <para> The license can be viewed with <command>make
          show-license</command>, and if it is considered appropriate,
          the line printed above can be added to
          <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> to indicate acceptance of
          the particular license:</para>

        <programlisting>ACCEPTABLE_LICENSES+=graphviz-license</programlisting>

	<para>When adding a package with a new license, the license
          text should be added to <filename>pkgsrc/licenses</filename>
          for displaying. A list of known licenses can be seen in this
          directory as well as by looking at the list of (commented
          out) <varname>ACCEPTABLE_LICENSES</varname> variable
          settings in
          <filename>pkgsrc/mk/defaults/mk.conf</filename>.</para>

	<para> If there is a <emphasis>really</emphasis> pressing need
          to accept all licenses at once, like when trying to download
          or mirror all distfiles or doing a bulk build to test if all
          packages in pkgsrc build, this can be done by setting
          <varname>_ACCEPTABLE=yes</varname>. 
	  </para>
      </sect2>
    

    <sect2>
      <title>Creating an account from a package</title>
    
      <para> There are two make variables used to control the creation
        of package-specific groups and users at pre-install time.  The
        first is <varname>PKG_GROUPS</varname>, which is a list of
        group[:groupid] elements, where the groupid is optional.  The
        second is <varname>PKG_USERS</varname>, which is a list of
        elements of the form: </para>
    
      <programlisting>user:group[:[userid][:[description][:[home][:shell]]]]</programlisting>
    
      <para> where only the user and group are required, the rest being
        optional.  A simple example is: </para>
    
      <programlisting>  PKG_GROUPS=       foogroup
    PKG_USERS=    foouser:foogroup</programlisting>
    
      <para>  A more complex example is that creates two groups and two
        users is:  </para> 
    
      <programlisting>  PKG_GROUPS=       group1 group2:1005
    PKG_USERS=    first:group1::First\\ User                      \
                  second:group2::Second\\ User:/home/second:${SH}</programlisting>
    
      <para> By default, a new user will have home directory
        <filename>/nonexistent</filename>, and login shell
        <filename>/sbin/nologin</filename> unless they are specified as
        part of the user element.  </para>
    
      <para> The package <filename>Makefile</filename> must also set
        <varname>USE_PKGINSTALL=YES</varname>. This will cause the users
        and groups to be created at pre-install time, and the admin will
        be prompted to remove them at post-deinstall time.  Automatic
        creation of the users and groups can be toggled on and off by
        setting the <varname>PKG_CREATE_USERGROUP</varname> variable
        prior to package installation.  </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Installing score files</title>
    
      <para> Certain packages, most of them in the games category, install
        a score file that allows all users on the system to record their
        highscores.  In order for this to work, the binaries need to be
        installed setgid and the score files owned by the appropriate
        group and/or owner (traditionally the "games" user/group).  The
        following variables, documented in more detail in
        <filename>mk/defaults/mk.conf</filename>, control this
        behaviour: <varname>SETGIDGAME</varname>,
        <varname>GAMEDATAMODE</varname>, <varname>GAMEGRP</varname>,
        <varname>GAMEMODE</varname>, <varname>GAMEOWN</varname>. </para>
    
      <para> Note that per default, setgid installation of games is
        disabled;  setting <varname>SETGIDGAME=YES</varname> will set all
        the other variables accordingly. </para>
    
      <para> A package should therefor never hard code file ownership or
        access permissions but rely on <varname>INSTALL_GAME</varname> and
        <varname>INSTALL_GAME_DATA</varname> to set these
        correctly. </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages providing login shells</title>
    
      <para>  If the purpose of the package is to provide a login shell,
        the variable  <varname>PKG_SHELL</varname> should contain the
        full pathname of the  shell executable installed by this
        package. The package  <filename>Makefile</filename> must also
        set  <varname>USE_PKGINSTALL=YES</varname> to use the
        automatically generated
        <filename>INSTALL</filename>/<filename>DEINSTALL</filename>
        scripts.  </para>
          
      <para> An example taken from shells/zsh: </para>
    
      <programlisting>  USE_PKGINSTALL=   YES
    PKG_SHELL=    ${PREFIX}/bin/zsh</programlisting>
    
      <para>
        The shell is registered into <filename>/etc/shells</filename>
        file automatically in the post-install target by the generated
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> script and removed in the deinstall
        target by the <filename>DEINSTALL</filename> script.  </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages containing perl scripts</title>
    
      <para>
        If your package contains interpreted perl scripts, set
        <varname>REPLACE_PERL</varname> to ensure that the proper
        interpreter path is set. <varname>REPLACE_PERL</varname> should
        contain a list of scripts, relative to
        <varname>WRKSRC</varname>, that you want adjusted.  </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages with hardcoded paths to other interpreters</title>
    
      <para>
        Your package may also contain scripts with hardcoded paths to
        other interpreters besides (or as well as) perl.  To correct the
        full pathname to the script interpreter, you need to set the
        following definitions in your <filename>Makefile</filename> (we
        shall use <command>tclsh</command> in this example):</para>
    
      <programlisting>  REPLACE_INTERPRETER+=     tcl
    _REPLACE.tcl.old=     .*/bin/tclsh
    _REPLACE.tcl.new=     ${PREFIX}/bin/tclsh
    _REPLACE_FILES.tcl=   ...list of tcl scripts which need to be fixed,
                          relative to ${WRKSRC}, just as in REPLACE_PERL</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing perl modules</title>
  
      <para>Makefiles of packages providing perl5 modules should include
        the Makefile fragment
        <filename>../../lang/perl5/module.mk</filename>.  It provides a
        <command>do-configure</command> target for the standard perl
        configuration for such modules as well as various hooks to tune
        this configuration.  See comments in this file for
        details.</para>
  
      <para>Perl5 modules will install into different places depending
        on the version of perl used during the build process.  To
        address this, pkgsrc will append lines to the
        <filename>PLIST</filename> corresponding to the files listed in
        the installed <filename>.packlist</filename> file generated by
        most perl5 modules.  This is invoked by defining
        <varname>PERL5_PACKLIST</varname> to a space-separated list of
        paths to packlist files, e.g.:</para>
  
      <programlisting>PERL5_PACKLIST=   ${PERL5_SITEARCH}/auto/Pg/.packlist</programlisting>
  
      <para>The variables <varname>PERL5_SITELIB</varname>,
        <varname>PERL5_SITEARCH</varname>, and
        <varname>PERL5_ARCHLIB</varname> represent the three locations
        in which perl5 modules may be installed, and may be used by
        perl5 packages that don't have a packlist.  These three
        variables are also substituted for in the
        <filename>PLIST</filename>.</para>
      </sect2>


    <sect2 id="faq.info-files">
      <title>Packages installing info files</title>
    
      <para>  Some packages install info files or use the
        <quote>makeinfo</quote>  or <quote>install-info</quote>
        commands. Each of the info files: </para>
    
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>is considered to be installed in the directory
            <filename>${PREFIX}/${INFO_DIR}</filename>,</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>is registered in the Info directory file
            <filename>${PREFIX}/${INFO_DIR}/dir</filename>,</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>and must be listed as a filename in the
            <varname>INFO_FILES</varname> variable in the package
            Makefile.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    
      <para> <varname>INFO_DIR</varname> defaults to <quote>info</quote>
        and can be overridden in the package
        Makefile. <filename>INSTALL</filename> and
        <filename>DEINSTALL</filename> scripts will be generated to
        handle registration of the info files in the Info directory
        file. The <quote>install-info</quote> command used for the info
        files registration is either provided by the system, or by a
        special purpose package automatically added as dependency if
        needed.  </para>
    
      <para> A package which needs the <quote>makeinfo</quote> command
        at build time must define the variable
        <varname>USE_MAKEINFO</varname> in its Makefile. If a minimum
        version of the <quote>makeinfo</quote> command is needed it
        should be noted with the <varname>TEXINFO_REQD</varname>
        variable in the package <filename>Makefile</filename>. By
        default, a minimum version of 3.12 is required. If the system
        does not provide a <command>makeinfo</command> command or if it
        does not match the required minimum, a build dependency on the
        <pkg>devel/gtexinfo</pkg> package will be added automatically.
        </para>
    
      <para> The build and installation process of the software provided
        by the package should not use the
        <command>install-info</command> command as the registration of
        info files is the task of the package
        <filename>INSTALL</filename> script, and it must use the
        appropriate <command>makeinfo</command> command.  </para>
    
      <para> To achieve this goal the pkgsrc infrastructure creates
        overriding scripts for the <command>install-info</command> and
        <command>makeinfo</command> commands in a directory listed early
        in <varname>PATH</varname>.  </para>
    
      <para> The script overriding <command>install-info</command> has
        no effect except the logging of a message. The script overriding
        <command>makeinfo</command> logs a message and according to the
        value of <varname>USE_MAKEINFO</varname> and
        <varname>TEXINFO_REQD</varname> either run the appropriate
        <command>makeinfo</command> command or exit on error.  </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing GConf2 data files</title>
    
      <para>
        If a package installs <filename>.schemas</filename> or
        <filename>.entries</filename> files, used by GConf2, 
        you need to take some extra steps to make sure they get registered
        in the database:
        </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> Include <filename>../../devel/GConf2/schemas.mk</filename>
          instead of its <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file.  This
          takes care of rebuilding the GConf2 database at installation and
          deinstallation time, and tells the package where to install
          GConf2 data files using some standard configure arguments.  It
          also disallows any access to the database directly from the
          package. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para> Ensure that the package installs its
          <filename>.schemas</filename> files under
          <filename>${PREFIX}/share/gconf/schemas</filename>.  If they get
          installed under <filename>${PREFIX}/etc</filename>, you will
          need to manually patch the package. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para> Check the PLIST and remove any entries under the etc/gconf
          directory, as they will be handled automatically.  See
          <xref linkend="faq.conf"/> for more information. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para> Define the <varname>GCONF2_SCHEMAS</varname> variable in
          your <filename>Makefile</filename> with a list of all
          <filename>.schemas</filename> files installed by the package, if
          any.  Names must not contain any directories in them. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para> Define the <varname>GCONF2_ENTRIES</varname> variable in
          your <filename>Makefile</filename> with a 
          list of all <filename>.entries</filename> files installed by the
          package, if any. Names must not contain any directories in
          them. </para> 
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing scrollkeeper data files</title>
    
      <para>
        If a package installs <filename>.omf</filename> files, used by
        scrollkeeper, you need to take some extra steps to make sure they
        get registered in the database:
        </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Include
            <filename>../../textproc/scrollkeeper/omf.mk</filename>
            instead of its <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file.  This
            takes care of rebuilding the scrollkeeper database at
            installation and deinstallation time, and disallows any access
            to it directly from the package.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para> Check the PLIST and remove any entries under the
            <filename>libdata/scrollkeeper</filename> directory, as they
            will be handled automatically. </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para> Remove the <filename>share/omf</filename> directory from
            the PLIST.  It will be handled by scrollkeeper. </para>
        </listitem>       
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing X11 fonts</title>
    
      <para> If a package installs font files, you will need to rebuild
        the fonts database in the directory where they get installed at
        installation and deinstallation time.  This can be automatically
        done by using <filename>mk/fonts.mk</filename>, which you need to
        include in your <filename>Makefile</filename>. </para>
    
      <para> When the file is included, you can list the directories where
        fonts are installed in the
        <varname>FONTS_<replaceable>type</replaceable>_DIRS</varname>
        variables, where <replaceable>type</replaceable> can be one of
        <quote>TTF</quote>, <quote>TYPE1</quote> or <quote>X11</quote>.
        Also make sure that the database file
        <filename>fonts.dir</filename> is not listed in the PLIST. </para>
    
      <para> Note that you should not create new directories for fonts;
        instead use the standard ones to avoid that the user needs to 
        manually configure his X server to find them. </para>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing GTK2 modules</title>
    
      <para>If a package installs gtk2 immodules or loaders, you need to
        take some extra steps to get them registered in the GTK2 database
        properly: </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
      <listitem> <para> Include
        <filename>../../x11/gtk2/modules.mk</filename> instead of its
        <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file.  This takes care of
        rebuilding the database at installation and deinstallation time.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem> <para>
        Set <varname>GTK2_IMMODULES=YES</varname> if
            your package installs GTK2 immodules. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem> <para>
        Set <varname>GTK2_LOADERS=YES</varname> if your package installs
            GTK2 loaders. </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem> <para>
        Patch the package to not touch any of the gtk2 databases directly.
        These are:
    
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><filename>libdata/gtk-2.0/gdk-pixbuf.loaders</filename></para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><filename>libdata/gtk-2.0/gtk.immodules</filename></para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem> <para>
        Check the PLIST and remove any entries under the
        <filename>libdata/gtk-2.0</filename> directory, as they will be
        handled automatically. </para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing SGML or XML data</title>
    
      <para> If a package installs SGML or XML data files that need to be
        registered in system-wide catalogs (like DTDs, sub-catalogs,
        etc.), you need to take some extra steps:
        </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Include
            <filename>../../textproc/xmlcatmgr/catalogs.mk</filename> in
            your <filename>Makefile</filename>, which takes care of
            registering those files in system-wide catalogs at
            installation and deinstallation time. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Set <varname>SGML_CATALOGS</varname> to the full path of
            any SGML catalogs installed by the package. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Set <varname>XML_CATALOGS</varname> to the full path of
            any XML catalogs installed by the package. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Set <varname>SGML_ENTRIES</varname> to individual entries
            to be added to the SGML catalog.  These come in groups of
            three strings; see xmlcatmgr(1) for more information
            (specifically, arguments recognized by the 'add' action).
            Note that you will normally not use this variable. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Set <varname>XML_ENTRIES</varname> to individual entries
            to be added to the XML catalog.  These come in groups of three
            strings; see xmlcatmgr(1) for more information (specifically,
            arguments recognized by the 'add' action).  Note that you will
            normally not use this variable.
            </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages installing extensions to the MIME database</title>
    
      <para> If a package provides extensions to the MIME database by
        installing <filename>.xml</filename> files inside
        <filename>${PREFIX}/share/mime/packages</filename>, you 
        need to take some extra steps to ensure that the database is kept
        consistent with respect to these new files:
        </para>
    
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para> Include
            <filename>../../databases/shared-mime-info/mimedb.mk</filename>
            (avoid using the <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> file from
            this same directory, which is reserved for inclusion from
            other <filename>buildlink3.mk</filename> files).  It takes
            care of rebuilding the MIME database at installation and
            deinstallation time, and disallows any access to it directly
            from the package. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Check the PLIST and remove any entries under the
            <filename>share/mime</filename> directory,
            <emphasis>except</emphasis> for files saved under 
            <filename>share/mime/packages</filename>.  The former are
            handled automatically by 
            the update-mime-database program, but the later are
            package-dependent and must be removed by the package that
            installed them in the first place. </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para> Remove any <filename>share/mime/*</filename> directories
            from the PLIST.  They will be handled by the shared-mime-info
            package. </para>
        </listitem>       
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    
    <sect2>
      <title>Packages using intltool</title>
    
      <para>   If a package uses intltool during its build, include the 
        <filename>../../textproc/intltool/buildlink3.mk</filename> file,
        which forces it to use the intltool package provided by pkgsrc,
        instead of the one bundled with the distribution file.
        </para>
    
      <para> This tracks intltool's build-time dependencies and uses the
        latest available version; this way, the package benefits of any
        bug fixes that may have appeared since it was released.
        </para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2>
        <title>Packages installing startup scripts</title>
        <para>If a package contains a rc.d script, it won't be copied into
        the startup directory by default, but you can enable it, by adding
        the option <varname>PKG_RCD_SCRIPTS=YES</varname> in
        <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>. This option will copy the scripts
        into <filename>/etc/rc.d</filename> when a package is installed, and
        it will automatically remove the scripts when the package is
        deinstalled.</para>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

    
  <sect1>
    <title>Feedback to the author</title>
    
    <para> If you have found any bugs in the package you make available,
      if you had to do special steps to make it run under NetBSD or
      if you enhanced the software in various other ways, be sure
      to report these changes back to the original author of the
      program! With that kind of support, the next release of the
      program can incorporate these fixes, and people not using the
      NetBSD packages system can win from your efforts. </para>

    <para> Support the idea of free software! </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
