<!-- $NetBSD: ftp-layout.xml,v 1.6 2006/09/18 12:16:25 rillig Exp $ -->

<appendix id="ftp-layout">
<title>Directory layout of the pkgsrc FTP server</title>

	<para>As in other big projects, the directory layout of pkgsrc
	is quite complex for newbies. This chapter explains where you
	find things on the FTP server. The base directory on
	<filename>ftp.NetBSD.org</filename> is <ulink
	url="ftp://ftp.NetBSD.org/pub/pkgsrc/"><filename>/pub/pkgsrc/</filename></ulink>.
	On other servers it may be different, but inside this directory,
	everything should look the same, no matter on which server you
	are. This directory contains some subdirectories, which are
	explained below.</para>

<sect1 id="ftp-bootstrap">
<title><filename>bootstrap-pkgsrc</filename>: Bootstrap kits</title>

	<para>For those who only want to manage binary packages on
	systems other than NetBSD, we provide the package management
	tools in a separate, small tar file.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="ftp-distfiles">
<title><filename>distfiles</filename>: The distributed source files</title>

	<para>The directory <filename>distfiles</filename> contains lots
	of archive files from all pkgsrc packages, which are mirrored
	here. The subdirectories are called after their package names
	and are used when the distributed files have names that don't
	explicitly contain a version number or are otherwise too generic
	(for example <filename>release.tar.gz</filename>).</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="ftp-iso">
<title><filename>iso</filename>: Currently empty</title>

	<para>This directory is currently not in use.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="ftp-misc">
<title><filename>misc</filename>: Miscellaneous things</title>

	<para>This directory contains things that individual pkgsrc
	developers find worth publishing.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="ftp-packages">
<title><filename>packages*</filename>: Binary packages</title>

	<para>These directories contain binary packages. Those
	directories that have a branch name
	(200<replaceable>x</replaceable>Q<replaceable>y</replaceable>)
	contain packages from that particular branch. The directory
	<filename>packages</filename> contains binary packages from
	pkgsrc-current. (However, this does not necessarily mean that
	the packages are still current anymore.)</para>

	<para>Below the <filename>packages*</filename> directories are
	directories that distinguish the packages by operating system
	and version, the next directory level specifies the hardware
	architecture.</para>

	<para>In each of the platform-specific directories, there is a
	whole binary packages collection. It has a directory called
	<filename>All</filename> which contains all binary packages.
	Besides that, there are various category directories that
	contain symbolic links to the real binary packages.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="ftp-source">
<title><filename>current</filename>,
<filename>200<replaceable>x</replaceable>Q<replaceable>y</replaceable></filename>:
source packages</title>

	<para>These directories contain the <quote>real</quote> pkgsrc,
	that is the files that define how to create binary packages from
	source archives.</para>

	<para>The directory <filename>pkgsrc</filename> contains a
	snapshot of the CVS repository, which is updated regularly. The
	file <filename>pkgsrc.tar.gz</filename> contains the same as the
	directory, ready to be downloaded as a whole.</para>

	<para>In the directories for the quarterly branches, there is an
	additional file called
	<filename>pkgsrc-200<replaceable>x</replaceable>Q<replaceable>y</replaceable>.tar.gz</filename>,
	which contains the state of pkgsrc when it was branched.</para>

</sect1>
</appendix>
