<!-- $NetBSD: makefile.xml,v 1.14 2005/05/15 23:46:20 rillig Exp $ -->

<!-- based on:
pkgsrc/bootstrap/bmake/for.c 1.1.1.1
pkgsrc/bootstrap/bmake/make.1 1.3
pkgsrc/bootstrap/bmake/str.c 1.1.1.1
pkgsrc/bootstrap/bmake/var.c 1.2
-->

<chapter id="makefile"> <?dbhtml filename="makefile.html"?>
  <title>Programming in <filename>Makefile</filename>s</title>

  <para>Pkgsrc consists of many <filename>Makefile</filename> fragments,
  each of which forms a well-defined part of the pkgsrc system. Using
  the &man.make.1; system as a programming language for a big system
  like pkgsrc requires some discipline to keep the code correct and
  understandable.</para>

  <para>The basic ingredients for <filename>Makefile</filename>
  programming are variables (which are actually macros) and shell
  commands. Among these shell commands may even be more complex ones
  like &man.awk.1; programs. To make sure that every shell command runs
  as intended it is necessary to quote all variables correctly when they
  are used.</para>

  <para>This chapter describes some patterns, that appear quite often in
  <filename>Makefile</filename>s, including the pitfalls that come along
  with them.</para>

  <sect1 id="makefile.variables">
    <title><filename>Makefile</filename> variables</title>

    <para><filename>Makefile</filename> variables contain strings that
    can be processed using the five operators ``='', ``+='', ``?='',
    ``:='', and ``!='', which are described in the &man.make.1; man
    page.</para>

    <para>When a variable's value is parsed from a
    <filename>Makefile</filename>, the hash character ``#'' and the
    backslash character ``\'' are handled specially. If a backslash is
    followed by a newline, any whitespace immediately in front of the
    backslash, the backslash, the newline, and any whitespace
    immediately behind the newline are replaced with a single space. A
    backspace character and an immediately following hash character are
    replaced with a single hash character. Otherwise the backslash is
    passed as is. In a variable assignment, any hash character that is
    not preceded by a backslash starts a comment that continues upto the
    end of the logical line.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Note:</emphasis> Because of this parsing algorithm
    the only way to create a variable consisting of a single backslash
    is using the ``!='' operator, for example: <!-- FIXME
    --><varname>BACKSLASH!=echo "\\"</varname>.</para>

    <para>So far for defining variables. The other thing you can do with
    variables is evaluating them. A variable is evaluated when it is
    part of the right side of the ``:='' or the ``!='' operator, or
    directly before executing a shell command which the variable is part
    of. In all other cases &man.make.1; performs lazy evaluation, that
    is, variables are not evaluated until there's no other way. The
    ``modifiers'' mentioned in the man page also evaluate the
    variable.</para>

    <para>Some of the modifiers split the string into words and then
    operate on the words, others operate on the string as a whole. When
    a string is splitted into words, it is splitted as you would expect
    it from &man.sh.1;.</para>

    <para>No rule without exception&mdash;the <command>.for</command>
    loop does not follow the shell quoting rules but splits at sequences
    of whitespace.</para>

    <para>There are several types of variables that should be handled
    differently. Strings and two types of lists.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem><para><emphasis>Strings</emphasis> can contain arbitrary
      characters. Nevertheless you should restrict yourself to only
      using printable characters. Examples are
      <varname>PREFIX</varname> and
      <varname>COMMENT</varname>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis>Internal lists</emphasis> are lists that
      are never exported to any shell command. Their elements are
      separated by whitespace. Therefore the elements themselves cannot
      have embedded whitespace. Any other characters are allowed.
      Internal lists can be used in <command>.for</command> loops.
      Examples are <varname>DEPENDS</varname> and
      <varname>BUILD_DEPENDS</varname>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis>External lists</emphasis> are lists that
      may be exported to a shell command. Their elements can contain any
      characters, including whitespace. That's why they cannot be used
      in <command>.for</command> loops. Examples are
      <varname>DISTFILES</varname> and
      <varname>MASTER_SITES</varname>.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2 id="makefile.variables.names">
      <title>Naming conventions</title>

      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>All variable names starting with an underscore
	are reserved for use by the pkgsrc infrastructure. They shall
	not be used by package
	<filename>Makefile</filename>s.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>In <command>.for</command> loops you should use
	lowercase variable names for the iteration
	variables.</para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="makefile.code">
    <title>Code snippets</title>

    <para>This section presents you with some code snippets you should
    use in your own code. If you don't find anything appropriate here,
    you should test your code and add it here.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Adding things to a list</title>

      <programlisting>
STRING=                 foo * bar `date`
INT_LIST=               # empty
ANOTHER_INT_LIST=       apache-[0-9]*:../../www/apache
EXT_LIST=               # empty
ANOTHER_EXT_LIST=       a=b c=d

INT_LIST+=              ${STRING}               # 1
INT_LIST+=              ${ANOTHER_INT_LIST}     # 2
EXT_LIST+=              ${STRING:Q}             # 3
EXT_LIST+=              ${ANOTHER_EXT_LIST}     # 4
      </programlisting>

      <para>When you add a string to an external list (example 3), it
      must be quoted. In all other cases, you must not add a quoting
      level. You must not merge internal and external lists, unless you
      are sure that all entries are correctly interpreted in both
      lists.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Converting an internal list into an external list</title>

      <programlisting>
EXT_LIST=       # empty
.for i in ${INT_LIST}
EXT_LIST+=      ${i:Q}""
.endfor
      </programlisting>

      <para>This code converts the internal list
      <varname>INT_LIST</varname> into the external list
      <varname>EXT_LIST</varname>. As the elements of an internal list
      are unquoted they must be quoted here. The reason for appending
      <varname>""</varname> is explained below.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Passing variables to a shell command</title>

      <programlisting>
STRING=         foo bar <    > * `date` $$HOME ' "
EXT_LIST=       string=${STRING:Q} x=second\ item

all:
        echo ${STRING}                  # 1
        echo "${STRING}"                # 2
        echo "${STRING:Q}"              # 3
        echo ${STRING:Q}                # 4
        echo x${STRING:Q} | sed 1s,.,,  # 5
        env ${EXT_LIST} /bin/sh -c 'echo "$$string"; echo "$$x"'
      </programlisting>

      <para>Example 1 leads to a syntax error in the shell, as the
      characters are just copied.</para>

      <para>Example 2 leads to a syntax error too, and if you leave out
      the last " character from <varname>${STRING}</varname>,
      &man.date.1; will be executed. The <varname>$HOME</varname> shell
      variable would be evaluated, too.</para>

      <para>Example 3 outputs each space character preceded by a
      backslash (or not), depending on the implementation of the
      &man.echo.1; command.</para>

      <para>Example 4 handles correctly every string that does not start
      with a dash. In that case, the result depends on the
      implementation of the &man.echo.1; command. As long as you can
      guarantee that your input does not start with a dash this form is
      appropriate.</para>

      <para>Example 5 handles even the case of a leading dash
      correctly.</para>

      <para>The <varname>EXT_LIST</varname> does not need to be quoted
      because the quoting has already be done when adding elements to
      the list.</para>

      <para>As internal lists shall not be passed to the shell, there is
      no example for it.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Quoting guideline</title>

      <para>There are many possible sources of wrongly quoted variables.
      This section lists some of the commonly known ones.</para>

      <itemizedlist>

	<listitem><para>Whenever you use the value of a list, think
	about what happens to leading or trailing whitespace. If the
	list is a well-formed shell expression you can apply the
	<varname>:M*</varname> modifier to strip leading and trailing
	whitespace from each word. The <varname>:M</varname> operator
	first splits its argument according to the rules of the shell,
	and then creates a new list consisting of all words that match
	the shell glob expression <varname>*</varname>, that is: all.
	One class of situations where this is needed is when adding a
	variable like <varname>CPPFLAGS</varname> to
	<varname>CONFIGURE_ARGS</varname>. If the configure script
	invokes other configure scripts it strips the leading and
	trailing whitespace from the variable and then passes it to the
	other configure scripts. But these configure scripts expect the
	(child) <varname>CPPFLAGS</varname> variable to be the same as
	the parent <varname>CPPFLAGS</varname>. That's why we better
	pass the <varname>CPPFLAGS</varname> value properly trimmed. And
	here is how we do it:</para>

        <programlisting>
CPPFLAGS=               # empty
CPPFLAGS+=              -Wundef -DPREFIX=\"${PREFIX:Q}\"
CPPFLAGS+=              ${MY_CPPFLAGS}

CONFIGURE_ARGS+=        CPPFLAGS=${CPPFLAGS:M*:Q}

all:
        echo x${CPPFLAGS:Q}x            # leading and trailing whitespace
        echo x${CONFIGURE_ARGS}x        # properly trimmed
        </programlisting></listitem>

	<listitem><para>The example above contains one bug: The
	<varname>${PREFIX}</varname> is a properly quoted shell
	expression, but there is the C compiler after it, which also
	expects a properly quoted string (this time in C syntax). The
	version above is therefore only correct if
	<varname>${PREFIX}</varname> does not have embedded backslashes
	or double quotes. If you want to allow these, you have to add
	another layer of quoting to each variable that is used as a C
	string literal. You cannot use the <varname>:Q</varname>
	operator for it, as this operator only works for the
	shell.</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>Whenever a variable can be empty the
	<varname>:Q</varname> operator can have surprising results. Here
	are two completely different cases which can be solved with the
	same trick.</para>

        <programlisting>
EMPTY=                  # empty
empty_test:
        for i in a ${EMPTY:Q} c; do \
                echo "$$i"; \
        done

for_test:
.for i in a:\ a:\test.txt
        echo ${i:Q}
        echo "foo"
.endfor
        </programlisting>

	<para>The first example will only print two of the three lines
	we might have expected. This is because
	<varname>${EMPTY:Q}</varname> expands to the empty string, which
	the shell cannot see. The workaround is to write
	<varname>${EMPTY:Q}""</varname>. This pattern can be often found
	as <varname>${TEST} -z ${VAR:Q}</varname> or as <varname>${TEST}
	-f ${FNAME:Q}</varname> (both of these are wrong).</para>

	<para>The second example will only print three lines instead of
	four. The first line looks like <varname>a:\ echo foo</varname>.
	This is because the backslash of the value
	<varname>a:\</varname> is interpreted as a line-continuation by
	&man.make.1;, which makes the second line the arguments of the
	&man.echo.1; command from the first line. To avoid this, write
	<varname>${i:Q}""</varname>.</para></listitem>

      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Workaround for a bug in BSD Make</title>

      <para>The pkgsrc bmake program does not handle the following
      assignment correctly. In case <varname>_othervar_</varname>
      contains a ``-'' character, one of the closing braces is included
      in <varname>${VAR}</varname> after this code executes.</para>

      <programlisting>
        VAR:= ${VAR:N${_othervar_:C/-//}}
      </programlisting>

      <para>For a more complex code snippet and a workaround, see the
      package <pkg>regress/make-quoting</pkg>, testcase
      <varname>bug1</varname>.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>
</chapter>
