<!-- $NetBSD: platforms.xml,v 1.9 2005/05/14 22:34:59 rillig Exp $ -->

<chapter id="platforms">
  <title>Using pkgsrc on systems other than &os;</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Bootstrapping pkgsrc</title>

    <para>For Operating Systems other than &os;, we provide a bootstrap kit to
      build the required tools to use pkgsrc on your platform. Besides
      support for native &os;, pkgsrc and the bootstrap kit have support for
      the following operating systems:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Darwin (Mac OS X)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>DragonFlyBSD</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>FreeBSD</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Interix (Windows 2000, XP, 2003)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>IRIX</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Linux</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>OpenBSD</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Solaris</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>Tru64 (Digital UNIX/OSF1)</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Support for other platforms is under development.</para>

    <para>Installing the bootstrap kit should be as simple as:</para>

    <screen>
&rprompt; <userinput>env CVS_RSH=ssh cvs -d anoncvs@anoncvs.NetBSD.org:/cvsroot checkout pkgsrc</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>cd pkgsrc/bootstrap</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>./bootstrap</userinput></screen>

    <para>See <xref linkend="getting"/> for other ways to get
      pkgsrc before bootstrapping. The given
      <command>bootstrap</command> command will use the defaults of
      <filename>/usr/pkg</filename> for the
      <emphasis>prefix</emphasis> where programs will be installed in,
      and <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename> for the package database
      directory where pkgsrc will do it's internal bookkeeping.
      However, these can also be set using command-line
      parameters.</para>

    <para>Binary packages for the pkgsrc tools and an initial set of packages is
      available for supported platforms. An up-to-date list of these can be
      found on <ulink url="http://www.pkgsrc.org/">www.pkgsrc.org</ulink>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Platform specific notes</title>

    <para>Here are some platform-specific notes you should be aware of.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Darwin (Mac OS X)</title>

      <para>Darwin 5.x and 6.x are supported. There are two methods of using
	pkgsrc on Mac OS X, by using a <link linkend="platform.osx-image">disk
	  image</link>, or a <link linkend="platform.osx-ufs">UFS
	  partition</link>.</para>

      <para>Before you start, you will need to download and install the Mac OS X Developer
	Tools from Apple's Developer Connection.  See <ulink
	  url="http://developer.apple.com/macosx/">http://developer.apple.com/macosx/</ulink>
	for details.  Also, make sure you install X11 for Mac OS X and the X11 SDK
	from <ulink
	  url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/download/">http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/download/</ulink>
	if you intend to build packages that use the X11 Window System.</para>

      <para>If you already have a UFS partition, or have a spare partition
	that you can format as UFS, it is recommended to use that instead of
	the disk image. It'll be somewhat faster and will mount automatically
	at boot time, where you must manually mount a disk image.</para>

      <note>
	<para>You cannot use a HFS+ file system for pkgsrc, because pkgsrc currently
	  requires the filesystem to be case-sensitive, and HFS+ is not.</para>
      </note>

      <sect3 id="platform.osx-image">
	<title>Using a disk image</title>

	<para>Create the disk image:</para>

	<screen>&rprompt; <userinput>cd pkgsrc/bootstrap</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>./ufsdiskimage create ~/Documents/NetBSD 512</userinput> # megabytes - season to taste
&rprompt; <userinput>./ufsdiskimage mount ~/Documents/NetBSD</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>sudo chown `id -u`:`id -g` /Volumes/NetBSD</userinput></screen>

	<para>That's it!</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="platform.osx-ufs">
	<title>Using a UFS partition</title>

	<para>By default, <filename>/usr</filename> will be on your root file
	  system, normally HFS+. It is possible to use the default
	  <emphasis>prefix</emphasis> of <filename>/usr/pkg</filename>
	  by symlinking <filename>/usr/pkg</filename> to a directory on a UFS
	  file system. Obviously, another symlink is required if you want to
	  place the package database directory outside the
	  <emphasis>prefix</emphasis>. e.g.</para>

	<screen>&rprompt; <userinput>./bootstrap --pkgdbdir /usr/pkg/pkgdb --pkgsrcdir /Volumes/ufs/pkgsrc</userinput></screen>

	<para>If you created your partitions at the time of installing Mac OS X
	  and formatted the target partition as UFS, it should automatically
	  mount on <filename>/Volumes/&lt;volume name&gt;</filename> when the
	  machine boots. If you are (re)formatting a partition as UFS, you need
	  to ensure that the partition map correctly reflects
	  <quote>Apple_UFS</quote> and not <quote>Apple_HFS</quote>.</para>

	<para>The problem is that none of the disk tools will let you touch a
	  disk that is booted from. You can unmount the partition, but even if
	  you newfs it, the partition type will be incorrect and the
	  automounter won't mount it. It can be mounted manually, but it won't
	  appear in Finder.</para>

	<para>You'll need to boot off of the OS X Installation (User) CD.  When
	  the Installation program starts, go up to the menu and select Disk
	  Utility.  Now, you will be able to select the partition you want
	  to be UFS, and Format it Apple UFS. Quit the Disk Utility, quit the
	  installer which will reboot your machine. The new UFS file system
	  will appear in Finder.</para>

	<para>Be aware that the permissions on the new file system will be writable
	  by root only.</para>

	<para>This note is as of 10.2 (Jaguar) and applies to earlier versions.
	  Hopefully Apple will fix Disk Utility in 10.3 (Panther).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>FreeBSD</title>

      <para>
	FreeBSD 4.7 and 5.0 have been tested and are supported, other versions
	may work.</para>

      <para>Care should be taken so that the tools that this kit installs do not conflict
	with the FreeBSD userland tools. There are several steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>FreeBSD stores its ports pkg database in
	    <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename>. It is therefore
	    recommended that you choose a different location (e.g.
	    <filename>/usr/pkgdb</filename>) by
	    using the --pkgdbdir option to the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If you do not intend to use the FreeBSD ports tools, it's probably a
	    good idea to move them out of the way to avoid confusion, e.g.</para>

	  <screen>&rprompt; <userinput>cd /usr/sbin</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_add pkg_add.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_create pkg_create.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_delete pkg_delete.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_info pkg_info.orig</userinput></screen>
</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>An example <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> file will be placed in
	    <filename>/etc/mk.conf.example</filename> file
	    when you use the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Interix</title>

      <para>Interix is a POSIX compatible subsystem for the Windows NT kernel,
	providing a Unix-like environment with a tighter kernel integration than
	available with Cygwin.  It is part of the Windows Services for Unix
	package, available for free for any licensed copy of Windows 2000, XP
	(not including XP Home), or 2003.  SFU can be downloaded from <ulink
	url="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/sfu/">http://www.microsoft.com/windows/sfu/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Services for Unix 3.5, current as of this writing, has been tested.  3.0
	or 3.1 may work, but are not officially supported.  (The main difference
	in 3.0/3.1 is lack of pthreads.)</para>

      <sect3 id="platform.interix-sfu-install">
	<title>When installing Interix/SFU</title>

	<para>At an absolute minimum, the following packages must be installed from
	  the Windows Services for Unix 3.5 distribution in order to use pkgsrc:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Utilities -&gt; Base Utilities</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Interix GNU Components -&gt; (all)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Remote Connectivity</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Interix SDK</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>When using pkgsrc on Interix, DO NOT install the Utilities subcomponent
	  "UNIX Perl".  That is Perl 5.6 without shared module support, installed to
	  /usr/local, and will only cause confusion. Instead, install Perl 5.8 from
	  pkgsrc (or from a binary package).</para>

	<para>The Remote Connectivity subcomponent "Windows Remote Shell Service" does
	  not need to be installed, but Remote Connectivity itself should be
	  installed in order to have a working inetd.</para>

	<para>Finally, during installation you may be asked whether to enable setuid
	  behavior for Interix programs, and whether to make pathnames default to
	  case-sensitive.  Setuid should be enabled, and case-sensitivity MUST be
	  enabled.  (Without case-sensitivity, a large number of packages including
	  perl will not build.)</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="platform.interix-sfu-postinstall">
	<title>What to do if Interix/SFU is already installed</title>

	<para>If SFU is already installed and you wish to alter these settings to work
	  with pkgsrc, note the following things.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To uninstall UNIX Perl, use Add/Remove Programs, select Microsoft
	      Windows Services for UNIX, then click Change.  In the installer, choose
	      Add or Remove, then uncheck Utilities-&gt;UNIX Perl.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To enable case-sensitivity for the filesystem, run REGEDIT.EXE, and
	      change the following registry key:</para>
	    <para>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Control\Session Manager\kernel</para>
	    <para>Set the DWORD value "obcaseinsensitive" to 0; then reboot.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To enable setuid binaries (optional), run REGEDIT.EXE, and change the
	      following registry key:</para>
	    <para>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Services for UNIX</para>
	    <para>Set the DWORD value "EnableSetuidBinaries" to 1; then reboot.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </sect3>      
      <sect3 id="platform.interix-notes">
	<title>Important notes for using pkgsrc</title>

	<para>The package imanager (either the pkgsrc "su" user, or the user
	  running "pkg_add") must be a member of the local Administrators
	  group.  Such a user must also be used to run the bootstrap.  This is
	  slightly relaxed from the normal pkgsrc requirement of "root".</para>

	<para>The package manager should use a umask of 002.  "make install" will
	  automatically complain if this is not the case.  This ensures that
	  directories written in /var/db/pkg are Administrators-group writeable.</para>

	<para>The popular Interix binary packages from http://www.interopsystems.com/
	  use an older version of pkgsrc's pkg_* tools.  Ideally, these should
	  NOT be used in conjunction with pkgsrc.  If you choose to use them at
	  the same time as the pkgsrc packages, ensure that you use the proper
	  pkg_* tools for each type of binary package.</para>

	<para>The TERM setting used for DOS-type console windows (including those
	  invoked by the csh and ksh startup shortcuts) is "interix".  Most systems
	  don't have a termcap/terminfo entry for it, but the following .termcap
	  entry provides adequate emulation in most cases:
          <programlisting>interix:kP=\E[S:kN=\E[T:kH=\E[U:dc@:DC@:tc=pcansi:</programlisting></para>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>IRIX</title>

      <para>You will need a working C compiler, either gcc or SGI's MIPS and MIPSpro
	compiler (cc/c89).  Please set the <varname>CC</varname> environment variable
	according to your preference.  If you do not have a license for the MIPSpro
	compiler suite, you can download a gcc tardist file from <ulink
	  url="http://freeware.sgi.com/">http://freeware.sgi.com/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Please note that you will need IRIX 6.5.17 or higher, as this is the earliest
	version of IRIX providing support for &man.if.indextoname.3;, &man.if.nametoindex.3;,
	etc.</para>

      <para>At this point in time, pkgsrc only supports one ABI.  That is, you can not
	switch between the old 32-bit ABI, the new 32-bit ABI and the 64-bit ABI.  If
	you start out using "abi=n32", that's what all your packages will be built
	with.</para>

      <para>Therefore, please make sure that you have no conflicting
	<varname>CFLAGS</varname> in your environment or the
	<filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>.  Particularly, make sure that you do not
	try to link n32 object files with lib64 or vice versa.  Check your
	<filename>/etc/compiler.defaults</filename>!</para>

      <para>If you have the actual pkgsrc tree mounted via NFS from a different host,
	please make sure to set <varname>WRKOBJDIR</varname> to a local directory,
	as it appears that IRIX linker occasionally runs into issues when trying to
	link over a network mounted filesystem.</para>

      <para>The bootstrapping process should set all the right options for programs such
	as imake(1), but you may want to set some options depending on your local
	setup.  Please see <filename>pkgsrc/mk/defaults/mk.conf</filename> and, of
	course, your compilers man pages for details.</para>

      <para>If you are using SGI's MIPSPro compiler, please set
         <programlisting>PKGSRC_COMPILER=mipspro</programlisting>
        in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>.  Otherwise, pkgsrc will assume you
        are using gcc and may end up passing invalid flags to the compiler.  Note that
        bootstrap should create an appropriate <filename>mk.conf.example</filename> by
        default.</para>

      <para>If you have both the MIPSPro compiler chain installed as well as gcc,
        but want to make sure that MIPRPro is used, please set your <varname>PATH</varname>
        to <emphasis>not</emphasis> include the location of gcc (often
        <filename>/usr/freeware/bin</filename>), and (important) pass the
        '--preserve-path' flag.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Linux</title>

      <para>
        Some versions of Linux (for example Debian GNU/Linux) need either
        libtermcap or libcurses (libncurses).  Installing the distributions
        libncurses-dev package (or equivalent) should fix the problem.</para>

      <para>
        pkgsrc supports both gcc (GNU Compiler Collection) and icc (Intel C++
        Compiler). gcc is the default. icc 8.0 and 8.1 on i386 have been tested.
      </para>

      <para>To bootstrap using icc, assuming the default icc installation
        directory:
        <programlisting>env CC=/opt/intel_cc_80/bin/icc LDFLAGS=-static-libcxa \
                ac_cv___attribute__=yes ./bootstrap</programlisting></para>

      <note>
        <para>icc 8.1 needs the `-i-static' argument instead of -static-libcxa.</para>
      </note>

      <para>icc supports __attribute__, but the GNU configure test uses a nested
        function, which icc does not support. #undef'ing __attribute__ has the
        unfortunate side-effect of breaking many of the Linux header files, which
        cannot be compiled properly without __attribute__. The test must be
        overridden so that __attribute__ is assumed supported by the
        compiler.</para>

     <para>After bootstrapping, you should set <varname>PKGSRC_COMPILER</varname>
        in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>:
        <programlisting>PKGSRC_COMPILER=icc</programlisting></para>

     <para>The default installation directory for icc is
        <filename>/opt/intel_cc_80</filename>, which
        is also the pkgsrc default. If you have installed it into a different
        directory, set <varname>ICCBASE</varname> in
        <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>:
        <programlisting>ICCBASE=/opt/icc</programlisting></para>

     <para>pkgsrc uses the static linking method of the runtime libraries
        provided by icc, so binaries can be run on other systems which do not
        have the shared libraries installed.</para>

     <para>Libtool, however, extracts a list of libraries from the &man.ld.1;
        command run when linking a C++ shared library and records it, throwing
        away the -Bstatic and -Bdynamic options interspersed between the libraries.
        This means that libtool-linked C++ shared libraries will have a
        runtime dependency on the icc libraries until this is fixed in libtool.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>OpenBSD</title>

      <para>OpenBSD 3.0 and 3.2 are tested and supported.</para>

      <para>Care should be taken so that the tools that this kit installs do not conflict
	with the OpenBSD userland tools. There are several steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>OpenBSD stores its ports pkg database in
	    <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename>. It is therefore
	    recommended that you choose a different location (e.g.
	    <filename>/usr/pkgdb</filename>) by
	    using the --pkgdbdir option to the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If you do not intend to use the OpenBSD ports tools, it's probably a
	    good idea to move them out of the way to avoid confusion, e.g.</para>

	  <screen>&rprompt; <userinput>cd /usr/sbin</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_add pkg_add.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_create pkg_create.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_delete pkg_delete.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_info pkg_info.orig</userinput></screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>An example <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename> file will be placed in
	    <filename>/etc/mk.conf.example</filename> file
	    when you use the bootstrap script. OpenBSD's make program uses
	    <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>
	    as well. You can work around this by enclosing all the pkgsrc specific parts 
	    of the file with:</para>

          <programlisting>.ifdef BSD_PKG_MK
# pkgsrc stuff, e.g. insert defaults/mk.conf or similar here
.else
# OpenBSD stuff
.endif</programlisting>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Solaris</title>

      <para>Solaris 2.6 through 9 are supported on both x86 and sparc. You will need a working C 
	compiler. Both gcc 2.95.3 and Sun WorkShop 5 have been tested.</para>

      <para>The following packages are required on Solaris 8 for the bootstrap
	process and to build packages.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>SUNWsprot</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>SUNWarc</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>SUNWbtool</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>SUNWtoo</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>SUNWlibm</para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Please note the use of GNU binutils on Solaris is
	<emphasis>not</emphasis> supported.</para>

      <sect3>
	<title>If you are using gcc</title>

	<para>It makes life much simpler if you only use the same gcc consistently
	  for building all packages.</para>

	<para>It is recommended that an external gcc be used only for bootstrapping,
	  then either build gcc from <pkg>lang/gcc</pkg> or install a binary gcc
	  package, then remove gcc used during bootstrapping.</para>

	<para>Binary packages of gcc can be found through <ulink
	    url="http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/common/freewareSearch.html">http://www.sun.com/bigadmin/common/freewareSearch.html</ulink>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title>If you are using Sun WorkShop</title>

	<para>You will need at least the following packages installed (from WorkShop
	  5.0)</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>SPROcc - Sun WorkShop Compiler C 5.0</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>SPROcpl - Sun WorkShop Compiler C++ 5.0</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>SPROild - Sun WorkShop Incremental Linker</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <para>SPROlang - Sun WorkShop Compilers common components</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>You should set <varname>CC</varname>, <varname>CXX</varname> and
	  optionally, <varname>CPP</varname> in <filename>/etc/mk.conf</filename>,
	  eg.</para>

        <programlisting>CC=     cc
CXX=    CC
CPP=    /usr/ccs/lib/cpp</programlisting>

	<para>You may also want to build 64-bit binaries, eg.</para>

        <programlisting>CFLAGS= -xtarget=ultra -xarch=v9</programlisting>

	<para>Whichever compiler you use, please ensure the compiler tools and
	  your $prefix are in your <varname>PATH</varname>. This includes
	  <filename>/usr/ccs/{bin,lib}</filename>
	  and eg. <filename>/usr/pkg/{bin,sbin}</filename>.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
