<!-- $NetBSD: platforms.xml,v 1.84 2013/11/15 10:11:47 asau Exp $ -->

<chapter id="platforms">
  <title>Using pkgsrc on systems other than &os;</title>

<sect1 id="binarydist">
<title>Binary distribution</title>

<para>See <xref linkend="using-pkg"/>.</para>

</sect1>

  <sect1 id="bootstrapping-pkgsrc">
    <title>Bootstrapping pkgsrc</title>

    <para>pkgsrc can be bootstrapped for use in two different modes:
    privileged and unprivileged one. In unprivileged mode in contrast
    to privileged one all programs are installed under one particular user
    and cannot utilise privileged operations (packages don't create
    special users and all special file permissions like setuid are ignored).
    </para>

    <para>Installing the bootstrap kit from source should be as simple as:</para>

    <screen>
&rprompt; <userinput>env CVS_RSH=ssh cvs -d anoncvs@anoncvs.NetBSD.org:/cvsroot checkout -P pkgsrc</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>cd pkgsrc/bootstrap</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>./bootstrap</userinput>
    </screen>

    <para>To bootstrap in unprivileged mode pass <quote>--unprivileged</quote> flag to <command>bootstrap</command></para>

    <para>By default, in privileged mode pkgsrc uses
    <filename>/usr/pkg</filename> for <emphasis>prefix</emphasis>
    where programs will be installed in,
    and <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename> for the package database
    directory where pkgsrc will do its internal bookkeeping,
    <filename>/var</filename> is used as <emphasis>varbase</emphasis>,
    where packages install their persistent data.
    In unprivileged mode pkgsrc uses
    <filename>~/pkg</filename> for <emphasis>prefix</emphasis>,
    <filename>~/pkg/var/db/pkg</filename> for the package database,
    and <filename>~/pkg/var</filename> for <emphasis>varbase</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>You can change default layout using command-line arguments.
    Run <quote>./bootstrap --help</quote> to get details.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>The bootstrap installs a <command>bmake</command> tool.
      Use this <command>bmake</command> when building via pkgsrc.
      For examples in this guide, use <command>bmake</command>
      instead of <quote>make</quote>.</para>
    </note>

    <note>
      <para>It is possible to bootstrap multiple instances of pkgsrc
      using non-intersecting directories. Use <command>bmake</command>
      corresponding to the installation you're working with to build
      and install packages.
      </para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="platform-specific-notes">
    <title>Platform-specific notes</title>

    <para>Here are some platform-specific notes you should be aware of.</para>

    <sect2 id="cygwin">
      <title>Cygwin</title>

      <para>Cygwin 1.7.x and later are supported.</para>

      <para>You need to install minimal base packages in `Base' category
      plus any of compiler, gcc, gcc4, and/or clang.
      For gcc and gcc4, C and C++ compiler will be installed by default,
      but you can install Fortran compiler additionally
      because it will be required to use libtool.
      If it is not installed (or too old), Fortran compiler will be
      installed with pkgsrc automatically.</para>

      <para>As noted in
      <ulink url="http://cygwin.com/faq-nochunks.html#faq.using.su">Cygwin FAQ: `Why doesn't su work?'</ulink>,
      su(1) command has been in Cygwin distribution, but it has never worked.
      Unless you bootstrap pkgsrc with the --unprivileged option, workaround is:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Right click "Cygwin Terminal" in your Start Menu,
          then pick "Run as administrator".</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="darwin">
      <title>Darwin (Mac OS X)</title>
      <!-- Mention which MacOS X versions this corresponds to! -->
      <para>Darwin 5.x and up are supported.</para>

      <para>Before you start, you need to download and install
      the Mac OS X Developer Tools from Apple's Developer Connection.
      This requires (free) membership. See
      <ulink url="http://developer.apple.com/macosx/">http://developer.apple.com/macosx/</ulink>
      for details. Also, make sure you install X11 (an optional
      package included with the Developer Tools) if you intend
      to build packages that use the X11 Window System.
      (If you don't want or need the full Xcode GUI,
      download and install Command Line Tools for Xcode.)</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="freebsd">
      <title>FreeBSD</title>

      <para>FreeBSD 8.3 and 9.0 have been tested and are supported,
      other versions may work.</para>

      <para>Care should be taken so that the tools that this kit installs do not conflict
      with the FreeBSD userland tools. There are several steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>FreeBSD stores its ports pkg database in
	  <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename>. It is therefore
	  recommended that you choose a different location (e.g.
	  <filename>/usr/pkgdb</filename>) by
	  using the --pkgdbdir option to the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If you do not intend to use the FreeBSD ports tools, it's probably a
	  good idea to move them out of the way to avoid confusion, e.g.</para>

	  <screen>
&rprompt; <userinput>cd /usr/sbin</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_add pkg_add.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_create pkg_create.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_delete pkg_delete.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_info pkg_info.orig</userinput>
	  </screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>An example &mk.conf; file will be placed in
	  <filename>/etc/mk.conf.example</filename> file
	  when you use the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="gnukfreebsd">
      <title>GNU/kFreeBSD</title>

      <para>Debian GNU/kFreeBSD is the only GNU/kFreeBSD distribution now.
      Debian GNU/kFreeBSD 7.0 or later is tested and supported.</para>

      <para> You should install ncurses (libncurses and libncurses-dev)
      packages.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="interix">
      <title>Interix</title>

      <para>Interix is a POSIX-compatible subsystem for the Windows NT kernel,
      providing a Unix-like environment with a tighter kernel integration than
      available with Cygwin.  It is part of the Windows Services for Unix
      package, available for free for any licensed copy of Windows 2000, XP
      (not including XP Home), or 2003.  SFU can be downloaded from <ulink
      url="http://www.microsoft.com/windows/sfu/">http://www.microsoft.com/windows/sfu/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Services for Unix 3.5 has been tested.  3.0 or 3.1 may work, but
      are not officially supported.  (The main difference in 3.0/3.1 is lack
      of pthreads, but other parts of libc may also be lacking.)</para>

      <para>Services for Unix Applications (aka SUA) is an integrated
      component of Windows Server 2003 R2 (5.2), Windows Vista and
      Windows Server 2008 (6.0), Windows 7 and Windows Server 2008 R2
      (6.1).  As of this writing, the SUA's Interix 6.0 (32bit) and
      6.1 (64bit) subsystems have been tested.  Other versions may
      work as well. The Interix 5.x subsystem has not yet been tested
      with pkgsrc.</para>

      <sect3 id="platform.interix-sfu-install">
	<title>When installing Interix/SFU</title>

	<para>At an absolute minimum, the following packages must be installed from
	the Windows Services for Unix 3.5 distribution in order to use pkgsrc:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Utilities -&gt; Base Utilities</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Interix GNU Components -&gt; (all)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Remote Connectivity</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Interix SDK</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>When using pkgsrc on Interix, DO NOT install the Utilities subcomponent
	"UNIX Perl".  That is Perl 5.6 without shared module support, installed to
	/usr/local, and will only cause confusion. Instead, install Perl 5.8 from
	pkgsrc (or from a binary package).</para>

	<para>The Remote Connectivity subcomponent "Windows Remote Shell Service" does
	not need to be installed, but Remote Connectivity itself should be
	installed in order to have a working inetd.</para>

	<para>During installation you may be asked whether to enable setuid
	behavior for Interix programs, and whether to make pathnames default to
	case-sensitive.  Setuid should be enabled, and case-sensitivity MUST be
	enabled.  (Without case-sensitivity, a large number of packages including
	perl will not build.)</para>

	<para>NOTE:  Newer Windows service packs change the way binary execution
	works (via the Data Execution Prevention feature).  In order to use
	pkgsrc and other gcc-compiled binaries reliably, a hotfix containing
	POSIX.EXE, PSXDLL.DLL, PSXRUN.EXE, and PSXSS.EXE (899522 or newer)
	must be installed.  Hotfixes are available from Microsoft through a
	support contract; however, Debian Interix Port has made most Interix
	hotfixes available for personal use from <ulink
	url="http://www.debian-interix.net/hotfixes/">http://www.debian-interix.net/hotfixes/</ulink>.</para>

	<para>In addition to the hotfix noted above, it may be necessary to
	disable Data Execution Prevention entirely to make Interix functional.
	This may happen only with certain types of CPUs; the cause is not fully
	understood at this time.  If gcc or other applications still segfault
	repeatedly after installing one of the hotfixes note above, the
	following option can be added to the appropriate "boot.ini" line on the
	Windows boot drive:  /NoExecute=AlwaysOff
	(WARNING, this will disable DEP completely, which may be a security
	risk if applications are often run as a user in the Administrators
	group!)</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="platform.interix-sfu-postinstall">
	<title>What to do if Interix/SFU is already installed</title>

	<para>If SFU is already installed and you wish to alter these settings to work
	with pkgsrc, note the following things.</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To uninstall UNIX Perl, use Add/Remove Programs, select Microsoft
	    Windows Services for UNIX, then click Change.  In the installer, choose
	    Add or Remove, then uncheck Utilities-&gt;UNIX Perl.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To enable case-sensitivity for the file system, run REGEDIT.EXE, and
	    change the following registry key:</para>
	    <para>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Control\Session Manager\kernel</para>
	    <para>Set the DWORD value "obcaseinsensitive" to 0; then reboot.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>To enable setuid binaries (optional), run REGEDIT.EXE, and change the
	    following registry key:</para>
	    <para>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Services for UNIX</para>
	    <para>Set the DWORD value "EnableSetuidBinaries" to 1; then reboot.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="platform.interix-notes">
	<title>Important notes for using pkgsrc</title>

	<para>The package manager (either the pkgsrc "su" user, or the user
	running "pkg_add") must be a member of the local Administrators
	group.  Such a user must also be used to run the bootstrap.  This is
	slightly relaxed from the normal pkgsrc requirement of "root".</para>

	<para>The package manager should use a umask of 002.  "make install" will
	automatically complain if this is not the case.  This ensures that
	directories written in /var/db/pkg are Administrators-group writeable.</para>

	<para>The popular Interix binary packages from http://www.interopsystems.com/
	use an older version of pkgsrc's pkg_* tools.  Ideally, these should
	NOT be used in conjunction with pkgsrc.  If you choose to use them at
	the same time as the pkgsrc packages, ensure that you use the proper
	pkg_* tools for each type of binary package.</para>

	<para>The TERM setting used for DOS-type console windows (including those
	invoked by the csh and ksh startup shortcuts) is "interix".  Most systems
	don't have a termcap/terminfo entry for it, but the following .termcap
	entry provides adequate emulation in most cases:</para>

	<programlisting>
interix:kP=\E[S:kN=\E[T:kH=\E[U:dc@:DC@:tc=pcansi:
	</programlisting>

      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="platform.interix-limits">
	<title>Limitations of the Interix platform</title>

	<para>Though Interix suffices as a familiar and flexible substitute
	for a full Unix-like platform, it has some drawbacks that should
	be noted for those desiring to make the most of Interix.</para>

	<itemizedlist>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">X11:</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Interix comes with the standard set of X11R6 client libraries,
	  and can run X11 based applications, but it does
	  <emphasis>not</emphasis> come with an X server.  Some options are
	  <ulink url="http://www.starnet.com/products/xwin32/">StarNet X-Win32</ulink>,
	  <ulink url="http://connectivity.hummingbird.com/products/nc/exceed/">Hummingbird Exceed</ulink>
	  (available in a trimmed version for Interix from Interop Systems as the
	  <ulink url="http://www.interopsystems.com/InteropXserver.htm">Interop X Server</ulink>),
	  and the free X11 server included with
	  <ulink url="http://x.cygwin.com/">Cygwin</ulink>.</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">X11 acceleration:</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Because Interix runs in a completely different NT subsystem from
	  Win32 applications, it does not currently support various X11
	  protocol extensions for acceleration (such as MIT-SHM or DGA).
	  Most interactive applications to a local X server will run
	  reasonably fast, but full motion video and other graphics
	  intensive applications may require a faster-than-expected CPU.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Audio:</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Interix has no native support for audio output.  For audio
	  support, pkgsrc uses the <command>esound</command> client/server
	  audio system on Interix.  Unlike on most platforms, the
	  <filename role="pkg">audio/esound</filename> package does
	  <emphasis>not</emphasis> contain the <command>esd</command>
	  server component.  To output audio via an Interix host, the
	  <filename role="pkg">emulators/cygwin_esound</filename> package
	  must also be installed.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">CD/DVDs, USB, and SCSI:</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Direct device access is not currently supported in Interix, so it
	  is not currently possible to access CD/DVD drives, USB devices,
	  or SCSI devices through non-filesystem means.  Among other things,
	  this makes it impossible to use Interix directly for CD/DVD
	  burning.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><emphasis role="strong">Tape drives:</emphasis></para>
	  <para>Due to the same limitations as for CD-ROMs and SCSI devices, tape
	  drives are also not directly accessible in Interix.  However,
	  support is in work to make tape drive access possible by using
	  Cygwin as a bridge (similarly to audio bridged via Cygwin's
	  esound server).</para></listitem>

	</itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="platform.interix-knownissues">
	<title>Known issues for pkgsrc on Interix</title>

	<para>It is not necessary, in general, to have a "root" user on the
	Windows system; any member of the local Administrators group will
	suffice.  However, some packages currently assume that the user
	named "root" is the privileged user.  To accommodate these, you
	may create such a user; make sure it is in the local group
	Administrators (or your language equivalent).</para>

	<para><command>pkg_add</command> creates directories of mode
	0755, not 0775, in <filename>$PKG_DBDIR</filename>.  For the
	time being, install packages as the local Administrator (or
	your language equivalent), or run the following command after
	installing a package to work around the issue:</para>

	<screen>
&rprompt; <userinput>chmod -R g+w $PKG_DBDIR</userinput>
	</screen>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="irix">
      <title>IRIX</title>

      <para>You will need a working C compiler, either gcc or SGI's MIPS and MIPSpro
      compiler (cc/c89).  Please set the <varname>CC</varname> environment variable
      according to your preference.  If you do not have a license for the MIPSpro
      compiler suite, you can download a gcc tardist file from <ulink
      url="http://freeware.sgi.com/">http://freeware.sgi.com/</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Please note that you will need IRIX 6.5.17 or higher, as this is the earliest
      version of IRIX providing support for &man.if.indextoname.3;, &man.if.nametoindex.3;,
      etc.</para>

      <para>At this point in time, pkgsrc only supports one ABI at a time.  That is, you cannot
	switch between the old 32-bit ABI, the new 32-bit ABI and the 64-bit ABI.  If
	you start out using "abi=n32", that's what all your packages will be built
	with.</para>

      <para>Therefore, please make sure that you have no conflicting
      <varname>CFLAGS</varname> in your environment or the
      &mk.conf;.  Particularly, make sure that you do not
      try to link n32 object files with lib64 or vice versa.  Check your
      <filename>/etc/compiler.defaults</filename>!</para>

      <para>If you have the actual pkgsrc tree mounted via NFS from a different host,
      please make sure to set <varname>WRKOBJDIR</varname> to a local directory,
      as it appears that IRIX linker occasionally runs into issues when trying to
      link over a network-mounted file system.</para>

      <para>The bootstrapping process should set all the right options for programs such
      as imake(1), but you may want to set some options depending on your local
      setup.  Please see <filename>pkgsrc/mk/defaults/mk.conf</filename> and, of
      course, your compiler's man pages for details.</para>

      <para>If you are using SGI's MIPSPro compiler, please set

      <programlisting>
PKGSRC_COMPILER=        mipspro
      </programlisting>

      in &mk.conf;.  Otherwise, pkgsrc will assume you
      are using gcc and may end up passing invalid flags to the compiler.  Note that
      bootstrap should create an appropriate <filename>mk.conf.example</filename> by
      default.</para>

      <para>If you have both the MIPSPro compiler chain installed as well as gcc,
      but want to make sure that MIPSPro is used, please set your <varname>PATH</varname>
      to <emphasis>not</emphasis> include the location of gcc (often
      <filename>/usr/freeware/bin</filename>), and (important) pass the
      '--preserve-path' flag.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="linux">
      <title>Linux</title>

      <para>Some versions of Linux (for example Debian GNU/Linux) need
      either libtermcap or libcurses (libncurses).  Installing the
      distributions libncurses-dev package (or equivalent) should fix
      the problem.</para>

      <para>pkgsrc supports both gcc (GNU Compiler Collection) and icc
      (Intel C++ Compiler). gcc is the default. icc 8.0 and 8.1 on
      i386 have been tested.</para>

      <para>To bootstrap using icc, assuming the default icc installation
      directory:</para>

      <programlisting>
env ICCBASE=/opt/intel/cc/10.1.008 ./bootstrap --compiler=icc
      </programlisting>

      <note>
	<para>For icc 8.0 you must add `LDFLAGS=-static-libcxa' to this.</para>
	<para>For icc 8.1 you must add `LDFLAGS=-i-static' instead.</para>
	<para>For icc 10.1 neither of these appears to be necessary.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Use a value for ICCBASE that corresponds to the directory
      where icc is installed. After bootstrapping, set
      <varname>ICCBASE</varname> in &mk.conf;:</para>

      <programlisting>
ICCBASE=                /opt/intel/cc/10.1.008
      </programlisting>

      <para>The pkgsrc default for <varname>ICCBASE</varname> is
      <filename>/opt/intel_cc_80</filename>. This is the default
      install directory for icc 8.0. If you are using a more recent
      version, be sure to set the correct path explicitly.
      </para>

      <para>pkgsrc uses the static linking method of the runtime libraries
      provided by icc, so binaries can be run on other systems which do not
      have the shared libraries installed.</para>

      <para>Libtool, however, extracts a list of libraries from the
      &man.ld.1; command run when linking a C++ shared library and
      records it, throwing away the -Bstatic and -Bdynamic options
      interspersed between the libraries.  This means that
      libtool-linked C++ shared libraries will have a runtime
      dependency on the icc libraries until this is fixed in
      libtool.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mirbsd">
      <title>MirBSD</title>

      <para>pkgsrc has been tested on MirBSD #10-current (2011 and newer).
      Older versions might also work. Releases before #10 are not
      supported.</para>

      <para>The package tools of the (older) native ports tree,
      <ulink url="//www.mirbsd.org/ports.htm">MirPorts</ulink>,
      have the same names as the ones used by pkgsrc. Care should be taken
      that the right tools are used. When installing packages from source,
      use the <filename>bmake</filename> command for pkgsrc and
      <filename>mmake</filename> for MirPorts.</para>

      <para>pkgsrc and MirPorts use the same location for the package
      database, <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename>. It is strongly recommended
      to use <filename>/usr/pkg/db</filename> instead, so that the pkgsrc
      tree is self-contained. This is also the default setting used in the
      binary package builds.</para>

      <para>Binary packages for MirBSD/i386 can be found on the pkgsrc ftp
      server. The bootstrap kit there already contains the
      <command>pkgin</command> package manager. See the
      <ulink url="https://www.mirbsd.org/pkgsrc.htm">pkgsrc on MirOS</ulink>
      page for more details.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="openbsd">
      <title>OpenBSD</title>

      <para>OpenBSD 5.1 has been tested and supported,
      other versions may work.</para>

      <para>Care should be taken so that the tools that this kit installs do not conflict
      with the OpenBSD userland tools. There are several steps:</para>

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>OpenBSD stores its ports pkg database in
	  <filename>/var/db/pkg</filename>. It is therefore
	  recommended that you choose a different location (e.g.
	  <filename>/usr/pkgdb</filename>) by
	  using the --pkgdbdir option to the bootstrap script.</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>If you do not intend to use the OpenBSD ports tools, it's probably a
	  good idea to move them out of the way to avoid confusion, e.g.</para>

	  <screen>
&rprompt; <userinput>cd /usr/sbin</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_add pkg_add.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_create pkg_create.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_delete pkg_delete.orig</userinput>
&rprompt; <userinput>mv pkg_info pkg_info.orig</userinput>
	  </screen>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>An example &mk.conf; file will be placed in
	  <filename>/etc/mk.conf.example</filename> file
	  when you use the bootstrap script. OpenBSD's make program uses
	  &mk.conf;
	  as well. You can work around this by enclosing all the pkgsrc-specific parts
	  of the file with:</para>

	  <programlisting>
.ifdef BSD_PKG_MK
# pkgsrc stuff, e.g. insert defaults/mk.conf or similar here
.else
# OpenBSD stuff
.endif
	  </programlisting>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="solaris">
      <title>Solaris</title>

      <para>Solaris 2.6 through 10 are supported on both x86 and sparc.
      You will need a working C compiler. Both gcc 4.5.3 and
      Sun WorkShop 5 have been tested.</para>

      <para>The following packages are required on Solaris 8 for the bootstrap
      process and to build packages.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>SUNWsprot</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SUNWarc</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SUNWbtool</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SUNWtoo</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SUNWlibm</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Please note that the use of GNU binutils on Solaris is
      <emphasis>not</emphasis> supported, as of June 2006.</para>

      <para>Whichever compiler you use, please ensure the compiler tools and
      your $prefix are in your <varname>PATH</varname>. This includes
      <filename>/usr/ccs/{bin,lib}</filename>
      and e.g. <filename>/usr/pkg/{bin,sbin}</filename>.</para>

      <sect3 id="solaris-gcc-note">
	<title>If you are using gcc</title>

	<para>It makes life much simpler if you only use the same gcc consistently
	for building all packages.</para>

	<para>It is recommended that an external gcc be used only for bootstrapping,
	then either build gcc from
	<filename role="pkg">lang/gcc46</filename> or install a binary gcc
	package, then remove gcc used during bootstrapping.</para>

	<para>Binary packages of gcc can be found through <ulink
	url="http://www.sunfreeware.com/"/>.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="solaris-sun-workshop-note">
	<title>If you are using Sun WorkShop</title>

	<para>You will need at least the following packages installed (from WorkShop
	5.0)</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>SPROcc
	  - Sun WorkShop Compiler C 5.0</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>SPROcpl
	  - Sun WorkShop Compiler C++ 5.0</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>SPROild
	  - Sun WorkShop Incremental Linker</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>SPROlang
	  - Sun WorkShop Compilers common components</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>You should set the following variables in your
	&mk.conf; file:</para>

<programlisting>
CC=     cc
CXX=    CC
CPP=    cc -E
CXXCPP= CC -E
</programlisting>

	<note><para>The <varname>CPP</varname> setting might break some
	packages that use the C preprocessor for processing things other
	than C source code.</para></note>

      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="solaris-sunpro-64">
	<title>Building 64-bit binaries with SunPro</title>

	<para>To build 64-bit packages, you just need to have the
	following lines in your &mk.conf; file:</para>

<programlisting>
PKGSRC_COMPILER=        sunpro
ABI=                    64
</programlisting>

	<note><para>This setting has been tested for the SPARC
	architecture. Intel and AMD machines need some more
	work.</para></note>

      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="plat.sunos.problems"><title>Common problems</title>

      <para>Sometimes, when using <command>libtool</command>,
      <filename>/bin/ksh</filename> crashes with a segmentation fault.
      The workaround is to use another shell for the configure
      scripts, for example by installing <filename
      role="pkg">shells/bash</filename> and adding the following lines
      to your &mk.conf;:</para>

      <programlisting>
CONFIG_SHELL=   ${LOCALBASE}/bin/bash
WRAPPER_SHELL=  ${LOCALBASE}/bin/bash
      </programlisting>

      <para>Then, rebuild the <filename
      role="pkg">devel/libtool-base</filename> package.</para>

      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
